<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A counter-plea to an apostataes [sic] pardon A sermon preached at Paules Crosse vpon Shroue-Sunday, February 15. 1617. By Robert Sibthorpe, preacher of the Word of God at Waterstratforde in Buckingamshire.</title>
            <author>Sybthorpe, Robert, d. 1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17950</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17950)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1083:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A counter-plea to an apostataes [sic] pardon A sermon preached at Paules Crosse vpon Shroue-Sunday, February 15. 1617. By Robert Sibthorpe, preacher of the Word of God at Waterstratforde in Buckingamshire.</title>
                  <author>Sybthorpe, Robert, d. 1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 [i.e. 55], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bar: Alsop, for Richard Fleming, and are to be sold at his shop at the great south-dore of Paules, on the right hand going vp the steps,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-H⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>P. 55 misnumbered 44.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with George Fairebeard as publisher in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17950:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17950:1"/>
            <p>A COVNTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLEA TO AN <hi>APOSTATAES</hi> Pardon.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT <hi>Paules Croſſe</hi> vpon Shroue-Sunday, <hi>February</hi> 15. 1617.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> ROBERT SIBTHORPE, Preacher of <hi>the Word of God at Waterſtratforde in</hi> Buckingamſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>IOHN 6.67.</bibl>
               <p>Will yee alſo goe away.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Si ante mortem non Reſipiſcant, haudquaquam ſaluatum iri arbitror.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iuſt: Martir: de veritate Chriſt: Relig:</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Bar: Alſop,</hi> for <hi>Richard Fleming,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the great South-door of Paules, on the right hand going vp the Steps. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17950:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17950:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR ARTHVR THROCKMORTON of <hi>Paulerſpury</hi> Knight, one of his Maieſties Iuſtices <hi>of the Peace and Coram in the County of Northampton; his</hi> religious, learned and vncorrupted Patron.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the common excuſe for the Preſſe is ouer-preſſing importunity, leſt the Authour ſhould ſeeme inexorable; although I might ſet that face on it, <hi>ſine fuco;</hi> yet I will rather acknowledge ingenuouſly, that the eſpeciall Apollogie for my preſumption is opportunity, leſt I might ſeeme vngratefull.</p>
            <p>Wherefore as al Riuers reuert vnto the Sea from whence they come:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.7.</note> So I returne this ſmall ſpring of the Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the immenſe Ocean of your bounty whence I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it.</p>
            <p>Which fauour although I had not receyued; yet (to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth without flattery: Amongſt all thoſe who
<pb facs="tcp:17950:3"/>haue vouchſafed the Sunne ſhine of their fauours vpon me, I know none ſo bleſſed in his owne integritie, his Ladies vertues, and his Ofſprings innocency, from thoſe ſinnes which are here cenſured, as that he might equally protect it without impeachment from thoſe muddy aſpertions which Sinne-ſhadowing Hypocrites may contend to caſt vpon it.</p>
            <p>Moſt humbly therefore beſeeching your Worſhippe to ſweeten this Current with your good acceptance, and to vouchſafe a Conduct pipe for it vnto others: with my prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for encreaſe of your happineſſe, continuance of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of yours, and imitation of them in others, I reſt.</p>
            <p>From your Worſhips Guift at <hi>VVaterſtratford,</hi> neere <hi>Buckingham.</hi> Feb. <hi>17.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips euer deuoted,</hi> Robert Sibthorpe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17950:3"/>
            <head>A COVNTERPLEA to an Apoſtataes Pardon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREM. 5.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>How ſhall I pardon thee for this? Thy Children haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken mee, and ſworne by thoſe that are no gods. And when I fed them to the full, they then committed Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and aſſembled themſelues by Troupes in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots houſes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EN, Fathers, and Brethren, Right Honourable, Right Worſhipfull, and Beloued: It is the poſition of the Apoſtle, that<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirituall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in high places;</hi> To which wee may adde the expoſition of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; That<note n="b" place="margin">Quis maior eſt populus cui miſcemur hinc periculi plus eſt. <hi>Seneca: Ep. 7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Corporall corruption is not ſequeſtred from great Aſſemblies:</hi> Wherfore being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to this high place, in this great Aſſembly, where is accuſtomed to be a concourſe, not onely from<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 13.44.</note> 
               <hi>all the parts of the City,</hi> but almoſt of<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>euery Nation vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi> I cald to mind this expoſtulation of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;<note n="e" place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4.5.</note> 
               <hi>Powerfull to beate downe the ſtrong holds, and euery thing that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God;</hi> whilſt it propoſeth the difficultie of an Apoſtataes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17950:4"/>Pardon; <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this? thy children haue forſaken me, and ſworne by thoſe that are no Gods, &amp;c.</hi> Profitable for the<note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>taming of the fieſh, and bringing it in ſubiection:</hi> whileſt it expoſeth the filthy ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and vngratefull filthineſſe of thoſe which are pampered with plenty of prouiſion: <hi>And when I fedde them to the full, by troupes they haunt Harlots houſes:</hi> A preſeruation of euery ſoule againſt ſinne: <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi> A caueat for Superiours, leaſt they licence others looſeneſſe. <hi>Thy children haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me?</hi> A ſalue againſt ſwearing, and Antidote for Idolatry: <hi>And ſworne by thoſe that are no Gods:</hi> A gage for Gluttony, and dyet againſt drunkenneſſe: <hi>When I fed them to the full:</hi> A preparatiue againſt Impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and a purge againſt vncleanneſſe. <hi>By Troupes they haunt Harlots houſes: How ſhall I pardon thee for this? Thy children haue forſaken me, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein omitting (as not applyable to the preſent) the Time wherein our Prophet preached,<note place="margin">Paraphraſis.</note> which<note n="g" place="margin">Hierom. l <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> in Ierem:</note> S. <hi>Hierom</hi> vpon infallible grounds affirmed to be <hi>Immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nente Captiuitate;</hi> as alſo ouer-ſlipping either generall <hi>Anal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis</hi> or argument of the Propheſie; wherein the Prophet declares with teares and lamentation the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and the captiuity of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their Idolatry, couetouſneſſe, ſubtilty, cruelty, exceſſe, rebellion, and contempt of Gods word (as the <hi>Geneuiſts</hi> obſerue) becauſe that as I could wiſh, that there were<note n="h" place="margin">Numb. 23 21. Ecclus. 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>no ſuch iniquity in Iacob,</hi> nor ſuch peruerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our <hi>Iſraell:</hi> So I will continually pray, that the<note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 4.19.</note> effect may be to them that hate vs, &amp; the application thereof to our enemies: Pretermitting (I ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17950:4"/>the premiſes, I will confine my conſiderations, not onely within compaſſe of this ſecond Sermon of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> as <hi>Tremelius</hi> ſtiles the 3.4.5. &amp; 6. Chapters of this Propheſie, but euen reſtraine them, <hi>Ad hanc terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am partem,</hi> as the aforeſaid Interpreter entituleth this Chapter. It being <hi>Confirmatio tum Peccati quod Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta Iudaeis exprobrat, tum ſupplicij denunciati,</hi> Both a conuincing of their preuaritation, and a confirming of their puniſhment: By reaſon that not onely all eſtates were attainted, but alſo euery particular perſon in a <hi>Praemunire.</hi> 1. For Eſtates: Firſt, the poore were not onely periured, ver. 2. <hi>Sed ne verecundiam quidem ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum habuere vitiorum,</hi> as (Saint <hi>Hieron,</hi>) They had made their faces harder then a Rocke with<note n="d" place="margin">Inſtar Petrae Indurentes frontes impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiae nolue u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ad meliora con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerti. Hieron. i Loc.</note> impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and refuſed to returne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Rich, <hi>Ianuam totius Licentiae, ſihi to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique populo aperirent,</hi> (as <hi>Trentelius</hi>) that for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren might forſake God, whileſt by how much the greater their authority was for ſuppreſſing; ſo imuch the more grieuous, their inſolency was in ſinning, (as Saint <hi>Hieron</hi>) ſo that they all had altogether broken the yoake, and burſt the bonds a ſunder, ver. 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And as for perſons, ſo vniuerſall was the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that vpon the ſtricteſt inquiſition, the Prophet could not finde out one that executed iudgement, and ſought truth, ver. 1. He could find ſome indeed, <hi>Qui ſimularent cultum Dei</hi> (as Saint <hi>Hieron</hi> ſayeth) who would carry a counterfeit forme of hypocriticall holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Though they they ſay the Lord liueth, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urely they ſweare falſely</note> and ſay, the Lord liueth: But if they were try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the touchſtone <hi>Veritatis &amp; Fidei,</hi> Of beleefe in their hearts, by the trueth of their Acts they ſhewed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17950:5"/>all was but falſely; Whereupon the Prophet in the perſon of the Almighty, inferres this ſeuenth verſe, as an<note n="b" place="margin">Trem: in loc.</note> exornation of the confirmation of their impiety &amp; puniſhment; and as a Catalogue of the ſinnes of the City; <hi>Dum dicit ſe ignorare Deus, qua poſcit eius occaſione miſereri,</hi> ſaith a Father, whilſt he breakes out into this Emphaticall Expoſtulation: <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein I will obſerue theſe two partes in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt an Expoſtulation; <hi>How ſhall I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thee for this?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Secondly, a Reaſon of the Expoſtulation: <hi>Thy children haue forſaken me, and</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which ſecond branch ſubdeuides it ſelfe into theſe two particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt, the Perſons, <hi>Thy Children.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Secondly, the ſins, <hi>Haue forſaken me,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which ſinnes are of a twofold Nature.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Capitall which is <hi>Apoſtaſie, Haue forſaken mee.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Criminall which accompany, <hi>And ſworn,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which are likewiſe fourefold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Swearing, <hi>Haue ſworne. And ſworne by,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2 Secondly, Idolatry, <hi>By thoſe that are no Gods. And ſworne by,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>3 Thirdly, Ingratitude, <hi>When I fed them to the full. And when I fed them,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>4 Fourthly, adultery, <hi>by troupes they aſſembled themſelues,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And when I fed them,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17950:5"/>
            <p> Which laſt particular affoordes two ſpeciall Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauations.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt their Impudency <hi>By troupes, they aſſembled themſelues by Troupes,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>2 Secondly, their Pertinacitie, <hi>They aſſembled,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they aſſembled themſelues by Troupes,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In moſt of which, although ſome haue beene ſo long rebellious that they are growne impudent,<note place="margin">Ezech. 2.3.4.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they and their fathers haue been accuſtomed to tranſgreſſe vntill this day, as the<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 1, 16.</note> Prophet aſſures mee; yet by Gods aſſiſtance, and your patience I will vtter my iudgement againſt them, touching all theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes.</p>
            <p>Wherein,</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Expoſtulation;<note place="margin">Part. 1.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ar: Mont,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tremel</hi> tranſlate it <hi>Vbi?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Where ſhall I finde a cauſe? <hi>Pagnin,</hi> and our Tranſlators render it <hi>Quomodo?</hi> How ſhall, &amp;c? Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> termes it, <hi>Super quo?</hi> In whom ſhall I finde occaſion. And all theſe Readings, as they may be borne without any repugnancy or the Texts rackt extenſion: So will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them not vnaptly affoorde vs matter of inſtruction.</p>
            <p n="1">1 And firſt <hi>(Vbi?)</hi> Where ſhall I finde a cauſe to pardon thee? As if he ſhould ſay, Shew mee but one place, one ſtreet, one houſe, in which the perfect feare of the Lord is, and I will pardon thee.</p>
            <p>Whereby is ſhadowed the willingneſſe of God,<note place="margin">Gods willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to mercy.</note> to ſhew mercy, rather then to execute iudgement vpon the ſonnes of men; which is intimated euen in the very Law, the ſeuereſt part of his Word, the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17950:6"/>of the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. And Inſtrument of death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5.10. Whileſt in the promulging of it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5.6. For viſiting ſinners vnto the third and fourth Generation, hee ſhewes mercy on them that loue him, vnto thouſands: For as the Pſalmiſt aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueres, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.5. Gratious is the Lord and righteous, yea, our God is mercifull; vpon which words, Saint <hi>Amb: Orat: de obitu Theodoſ: Bis Miſcricordiam poſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſemel Iuſtitiam;</hi> Signifying that he was twiſe ſo prone to pardon as to puniſhing: Yea <hi>Exod:</hi> 34.6.7. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe divulging his owne deſcription, proclaimes ſixe attributes of mercy for two of Iuſtice; which is Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blematically repreſented to vs in a two-fold paſſage of ſacred Scripture; The one, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.20.<note n="d" place="margin">Expende quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit lenta neque tarda di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine miſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or dia, adſubuent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum compunc tis corde Stella in Luc. <hi>15.</hi> Non tantum procederet obu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> am vententi, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etiam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreret: Ianſen</note> In the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Prodigall, who runnes to meete his retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſonne, as if hee longed to be at him, to ſhew his loue and compaſſion: The other, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8. At the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting <hi>Adam</hi> out of <hi>Eden</hi> where God walked, onely a ſlow pace, as the Originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> imports, as if hee were loath to bee too ſoone and ſwift in indignation; when hee was to ſhew mercy: <hi>Cucurrit,</hi> he ranne, as reioycing in it; but when to execute Iudgement, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulauit,</hi> he walked, as grieued and penſiue for it; <hi>Deus enim triſtatur, non de ſua iniuria, ſed de noſtra perditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi> Not for his loſſe, but for our looſing, not for his want, but for our woe; not for need of our ſubiection, but for our needleſſe ſubuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Whereupon here he makes this inquiſition, <hi>(V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi)</hi> Where ſhall I finde a cauſe to pardon thee?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Yea, that which is yet more; If thou canſt not ſhew mee a place; yet finde mee out one perſon, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17950:6"/>whom I may finde integrity, and I will take that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to pardon all the City: <hi>(Super quo?)</hi> In whom ſhall I doe it? Runne yee too and fro, through the ſtreetes of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and ſee, and know, and ſeeke in the broad places thereof, if you can finde one man, if there bee any that executeth iudgement, and ſeeketh trueth, and I will pardon it, v. 1. Whereout as we may conceiue <hi>Grandis amor iuſtitiae,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierom:</hi> How great the loue of God is to innocency;<note place="margin">Gods loue of Innocency.</note> when not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to <hi>Abrahams</hi> Petition for fifty, forty, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, twenty, or ten iuſt perſons, hee will ſpare <hi>Sodome,</hi> but euen after his owne Eſſentiall inclination; for one righteous man he will pardon <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. So alſo hereout the prophaner ſort may ſee,<note place="margin">Gods fauour for the faithfull ſake.</note> as in a mirrour repreſented vnto them, the vndeſerued fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors which are ſhowred vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments which are preuented &amp; auerted from them not for their owne ſakes, but often times for thoſe few deuout ſoules ſakes which feare God &amp; dwel amongſt them; <hi>All Labans flockes bleſſed for one Holy Iacobs ſake,</hi> Gen. 30.27. <hi>The whole houſe of Putiphar bleſſed for one righteous Ioſephs ſake,</hi> Gen. 39.5. Yea euen <hi>the Priſon proſpered for his Piety,</hi> ver. 23. As alſo <hi>Sodoms puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prolonged for one iuſt Lot,</hi> Gen. 19.22. <hi>Iſraels plague appeaſed for one deuout Phinehas,</hi> Pſal. 106.30. <hi>And their deſtruction diuerted for one faithfull Moſes,</hi> v. 23. Together with the earneſtneſſe of this Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may ſufficiently ſatisfie on all parts touching the ſoliditie of this aſſertion.</p>
            <p>Whereout as we may take vp Saint <hi>Bernards</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, <hi>Quam diues es in Miſericordia, et magnificus
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17950:7"/>in iuſtitia, et munificus in gratia, Domine, Deus noſter!</hi> Oh how rich art thou in mercy, how magnificent in iuſtice, and how munificent in grace, O Lord our God! There is none that is like vnto thee; <hi>Munerator copioſiſſimè, Remunerator aequiſſimè, Liberator piiſſimè:</hi> O moſt bountifull beſtower of celeſtiall inclinations, O moſt righteous rewarder of humane actions, O moſt diuine deliuerer from Diabolic all deſtruction: <hi>Gratis reſpicis, humilis inſtè iudicas innocentes, Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorditer etiam ſaluas peccatores,</hi> Who reſpecteſt the humble for thine owne mercy, not his merit, who iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iudgeſt the innocent, in thy fauour not thy fury; and mercifully ſaueſt the ſinner, for thy ſufferings, not his ſatisfaction, by his faith, not his fidelity: <hi>Oh what ſhall I returne vnto thee for ſo ineffable fauours beſtowed vpon me, I will take the cup of ſaluation and giue thankes vnto thee my God.</hi> Pſal. 116, 11.12. <hi>Who when there was none righteous vpon earth,</hi> Pſal. 14.4.<note n="c" place="margin">Iuſtitia de Coelo proſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> tan <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis parca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Aug ſuper Pſal <hi>84.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hath ſent one downe from Heauen, and ſo hath found a meanes how to pardon me for this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 And as here hence we muſt take out that <hi>Sibillae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sawe:</hi>
               <q>Diſeite iuſtitiam moniti, et non temnere Diuos.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 So muſt we take heed that our harts neuer turn, ſo that <hi>we hate Gods people, nor deale vntruly with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</hi> Pſal. 105.25. Who may truely ſay to licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Libertines,<note n="f" place="margin">Tertul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulam, c. <hi>4.</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Aurelius in G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ca expedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um militum oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ad Deum fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bres in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> petrauit, &amp;c.</note> as the Chriſtians to that Ethnicke Conſull in <hi>Tertullian, Quoties ieiuniis et geniculationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus noſtris etiam ſiccitates ſunt depulſae?</hi> How often haue our prayers like<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>Eliahs</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. Reg 3.36</note>, <hi>opened the dores of Heauen, to draw downe the former and later raine, to</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Math. 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>procure the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17950:7"/>ſunne to ſhine on the euill as well as good? to be a meanes of all good things to you that hated goodneſſe?</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 105.15</note> 
               <hi>Touch not his annointed, nor doe his Prophetes no harme: For hee that toucheth them, toucheth the Apple of his owne eye,</hi> Ez. 2 8. <hi>And right deare in the ſight of the Lord ſhall be the bloud of ſuch Saints.</hi> And how ſhall hee pardon thee for it?</p>
            <p n="4">4 And laſtly, ſince this <hi>Vera Miſericordia</hi> (as Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> cals it) is onely effected: <hi>Vt iuſtitia per cam non contemnatur,</hi> That Iuſtice by it is not neglected; Therefore let vs take heede that wee abuſe not Gods mercy, <hi>to ſcoffe at his iudgements,</hi> 2. Pet. 3.4. Nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume on his patience, to perſeuer in impiety; <hi>when it ſhould inuite vs to repentance,</hi> Rom. 2.3. But as we finde, <hi>That the Lord hath no pleaſure in the death of him that dyes,</hi> Ezec. Chap. 33. V. 11. But rather would that <hi>none ſhould periſh, but that alſhould come to repentance,</hi> 2. Pet. 3 9. So let vs reciprocally contend to bring forth<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 3, 7.8</note> 
               <hi>fruits anſwerable to amendment,</hi> Act. 26.20. That ſo we may be meet for mercy. For<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 85.10.</note> 
               <hi>behold onely mercy and truth ſhall meet together;</hi> onely <hi>Righteouſneſſe and Peace ſhall kiſſe each other:</hi> And therefore as he ſeekes,<note place="margin">Gods iuſtice ioynde with his mercy.</note> ſo let vs ſhew how he may pardon vs for this?</p>
            <p>In which Interrogation, <hi>Summe iuſtus et ſumme mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericors eſſe oſtenditur</hi> (as <hi>Zigedine</hi>) Mercifull, becauſe hee would pardon exorbitant ſinnes; Iuſt, becauſe he will be ſatisfied. <hi>(How?)</hi> at the hands of Sinners.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Quomodo? How ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay to thoſe which perſeuere in impenitent preſumptions offending. Behold, I will make your ſelues Iudges, and ſee if you can deuiſe a meanes how
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17950:8"/>I ſhall pardon you for it. <hi>The Iudge of all the Earth muſt needes doe right,</hi> Gen. 18.25. <hi>That he may bee iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied when he ſpeakes, and cleare when he is iudged,</hi> Pſ. 51.4. (.i.) <hi>Cum homines de illo iudicant, Hieron. Sauanorol:</hi> when men would paſſe their opinions on his proceedings as partiall they may finde no fault at all:<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 32.4</note> 
               <hi>A God of truth without iniquity, iuſt and right, and of</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Habak. 1, 13</note> 
               <hi>pure eyes that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure the ſight of euill:</hi> As<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 34.7.</note> mercifull in forgiuing iniquities and ſins; ſo iuſt in not clearing the guilty; whereas, if he ſhould pardon, when man preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly perſeueres in ſinne: what a prepoſterous courſe were that of iuſtice? Who might not condemne him, and ſay, <hi>That he was euen like one of them,</hi> Pſal. 50.21. (.i.) <hi>Scelerum patronus et approbator,</hi> A Patrone and approuer of ſinne. (as <hi>Mollerus</hi>) <hi>Si enim Deus impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos demitteret Males, ſimilis iniuſtorum inueniretur</hi> (as <hi>Haymo</hi> vpon the ſame place) How therefore is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for me to pardon thee? If thou beeſt not an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, but beleeueſt that God is, Then muſt thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge by neceſſary conſequence, that <hi>He is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder,</hi> Heb. 11.6. <hi>Both of the righteous and of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> Pſ. 11.5. <hi>Rendring to the one glory, honor and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life,</hi> Rom. 2.7. And to the other, <hi>Indignation, wrath, tribulation and anguiſh.</hi> Ver. 8.9. And therefore if a ſinner will not conuert and change himſelfe by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, It is as poſſible to change and alter Gods Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Eſſence, as to<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 7.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>eſcape the Inſtrument of death prepared for him.</hi> It is as poſſible <hi>(Abſit Blaſphemia verbo)</hi> for God to bee vniuſt, as the obſtinate vniuſt perſon to bee pardoned, whileſt hee continues vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17950:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which mee thinkes might ſtrike ſuch terrour and aſtoniſhment into the moſt obdurate Creatures (who had not like the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>Poole ſayde in their hearts, there is no God,</hi> and thereby giuen ouer themſelues vnto corrupt imaginations; That like<note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Belſhazar, their countenance ſhould be changed, and their thoughts troubled ſo, that their ioynts ſhould bee looſed, and their knees ſmite one againſt another:</hi> Seeing that wee which are the lighteſt and ſlighteſt part of the earth, euen<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>duſt and aſhes,</hi> may ſooner turne heauen and earth at our pleaſures; yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 93.1.</note> him that made and orders all; then wee can giue a counter-blaſt vnto one<note n="e" place="margin">Math. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>iot or title of his Word,</hi> which like the<note n="f" place="margin">Dan. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>Law of the Medes and Perſians may not be altered;</hi> or put a Ieofayle to his iuſtice, whoſe iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is like the great deepe, and his trueth firme as the mountaines.</p>
            <p>I would know of the cunningeſt excuſer of Sathans ſlights; how, when<note n="g" place="margin">Cor. 5.10</note> 
               <hi>all ſhall appeare before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Chriſt to receyue according to the things that they haue done in the fleſh;</hi> When<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5</note> 
               <hi>all things that haue been long hid in darkeneſſe ſhall bee brought to light, and the thoughts of euery mans heart ſhall be made manifeſt,</hi> when<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 2.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>Euery mans conſcience ſhall beare witneſſe, and their thoughts accuſe them according to this Goſpell:</hi> And when as <hi>Math.</hi> 26.59.60. To put Chriſt to death, they <hi>ſought many witneſſes but found none</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Many bare falſe witneſſe againſt him, but theyr wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe agreede not together. Mar. 14.56.59</note> 
               <hi>agreeing, vntill at the length the high Prieſt out of malice ſought to ſentence him out of his owne mouth,</hi> Ver. 65. So on the contrary to ſaue mans ſoule, all courſes ſhall bee excogitated, and none found conſonant to Iuſtice: And at the length
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17950:9"/>God in his mercy ſhall refer it to the ſinners own ſelfe, to deuiſe a way for his deliuery, <hi>With how ſhall I pardon thee for this?</hi> I would know, I ſay, with what face hee can affront him, or what anſwere hee can affoord him, if he haue not by<note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.31</note> 
               <hi>iudging himſelfe for vniuſtice,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Illam ergo diem fratres chariſsimi tota <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>entione cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, vit am cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigite, mores mutate, mala tentamina reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cite, Perpetrata au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem fletibus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite &amp;c. Greg. mag, hom. <hi>1.</hi> in Euang.</note> 
               <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by repentance the face of that moſt iuſt Iudges ſeuere ſentence: Certè turpis aut nulla in Die Iuaicii erit excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio</hi> (ſayth Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) Surely, eyther confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſhame the ſinner ſhall ſtand ſpeechleſſe, Mat. 22.12. Or <hi>ex ore tuo te iudicabo ſerue nequam,</hi> Luc. 19 22. His Apologie ſhall bee but the further plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his impiety, and his excuſe aggrauate his accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But peraduenture ſome who thinkes it not yet full time to take his leaue of the ſweet delights of ſinne, &amp; is of ſufficient capacity to cozen his owne ſoule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> Repentance deferred.</note> may ſecretly ſeem to haue ſpied this ſtarting hole; although I ſinne a long ſeaſon, yet I will repent at the laſt, and then I am not preiudiced for my pardon: For<note n="n" place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note> 
               <hi>at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſinnes from the bottome of his heart, I will put all his wickedneſſe out of my remembrance,</hi> ſayth the Lord.</p>
            <p>To whom, let this ſolution ſatisfie, Beſides that in that place, <hi>Ezec.</hi> 18.20.21. which is the place pretended (Or I know no other) It is required, that repentance be fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottome of the heart, <hi>Et ſerararò ſeria</hi> (as Saint<note n="o" place="margin">Multos ſolet ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ma poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia decipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aug:</hi>) That which is late is ſeldom liuely, but onely pretended, and not intended; Like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> during the preſent plague, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.27. Or <hi>Antiochus</hi> in his extremity, 2. <hi>Math,</hi> 9.7. Beſides this (I ſay) which is ſeldome ſeene<note n="p" place="margin">Luc. 23.43</note> and but once inſtaned in ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17950:9"/>Once, to the end that none deſpayre, and yet but once that none prefume: In the forenamed Text of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> there is adioyned <hi>Doing: If hee keepe my ſtatutes and do that which is lawful and right;</hi> which muſt neceſſarily inferre a Concluſion againſt deferring Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, vntill the time of mans diſſolution: for what doing, what worke, what deuice, what knowledge, what wiſdome is there in the graue? whether thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.20. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>
               </label> And therefore this muſt infallably im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a ſpeedy repentance, which may bee further enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, 1. Not only from the<note n="q" place="margin">Si quis poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in extrema neceſſitate ſuae agritudin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerit accipere Poenitentiam &amp; accipit ciſi fateor vobis non illi neganius quod petit, ſed nec praeſumimus quod bene hine exit. Aug: de Mir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſacr: Scrip.</note> inconuenience of chooſing out the end of ſicknes for the beginning of repentance When as Saint <hi>Aug: lbi rapitur intenſio mentis, vbi vis doloris:</hi> The minds Meditation is diſtracted to the place where the body is diſturbed: 2. Not only from the<note n="r" place="margin">Quem morbus vrget, &amp; poena terret, ad vera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vix veniet, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactionem. Maxime cum ſilij quos illicite dilexit ſint praeſentes vxor &amp; Mundus ad ſe vocet: Aug: ſer. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> inhability of a crazed Creature, to vndergoe ſo great a burden, and numberleſſe number of ſighes, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, troubles, teares, watchings, faſtings, prayers, perils, conflicts, conferences, and conſultations, as the ſtrongeſt body in the perfecteſt ſtate (vnleſſe God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it) is not ſufficient for. 3 But alſo from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of mans repenting at his own pleaſure.<note n="ſ" place="margin">In culpam incidiſſe naturae eſt, Dolere vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis: Amb: l. <hi>1</hi> de Dauid.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance being a grace of God, and not a gift of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: For there is no man that hath power ouer the Spirit, to receyue the Spirit, neyther hath he power in the day of death, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.8. <hi>There may be indeed a kind of ſorrow or heauines in man,</hi> 2. Cor. 7.10. which is, but (like a Melancholy paſſion forerunning a miſfortune) the Prelude to eternall vnhappineſſe; But to haue a godly ſorrow; Repentance not to be repented of (as in the ſame place the Apoſtle diſtinguiſheth) <hi>It muſt be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17950:10"/>of God,</hi> Act. 11.28. <hi>By the Prince and Sauiour of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, Act.</hi> 5.31. But as a Father hath religiouſly obſerued, <hi>Qui promiſit paenitenti veniam, non promiſit delinquenti pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam;</hi> Hee that promiſed pardon vnto the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, neuer promiſed repentance to the wilfull delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, neyther hath he giuen protection, <hi>Peccandi in craſtinum,</hi> vnto the perſeuering ſinner: And therfore take heed, leſt by deferring, as if thou deſpiſeſt Gods goodneſſe and patience, <hi>which ſhould leade thee to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> Rom. 2.4. Thou at the length reape vnto thy ſelfe <hi>a hard and reprobate heart which cannot repent,</hi> Ver. 5. <hi>Which is neyther vniuſt with God, as</hi> Rom. 1.24. The Apoſtle laies down the Axiom: Nor <hi>vnaccuſtomed to miſerable men,</hi> as <hi>Exod,</hi> 10.20. <hi>Preſumptuous Pharaoh,</hi> Heb. 12.17. <hi>Prophane Eſau.</hi> Ioh. 12.40. <hi>Apoſtatical Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> are ſet forth for fearefull examples: Preſume not therefore on Gods mercy to binde one ſinne vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, <hi>for in one thou ſhalt not goe vnpuniſhed,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.8. <hi>Vis ergo liberari? Paenitentiam age, dum ſanus es,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Wilt thou be aſſured of deliuerance, then repent whilſt thou art in health and proſperity, and hearten not thy ſelfe by thy former ſinnes, nor ſay not I haue ſinned; &amp; what harme hath come vnto me, and therefore I will ſtill doe ſo; for although the Lord be long ſuffering, yet in no wiſe hee will let thee goe: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>For though a Sinner doe euill a hundred times, &amp; his dayes be prolonged, yet it ſhall not bee well with him at the laſt, <hi>but he ſhall be cut off as a ſhadow,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.13. For if he dealt ſo with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as potent as thee in power: If ſo with <hi>Eſau,</hi> as importunate as thee in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17950:10"/>prayer. If ſo with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as inward as thee in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>How ſhall hee pardon thee for this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue beene ſpoken touching the firſt part which is the Expoſtulation; now we deſcend vnto the ſecond, which is the reaſon; <hi>Thy children haue forſaken mee, and ſworne by thoſe that are no Gods,</hi> &amp;c. And therein,<note place="margin">Part. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of the perſons <hi>(Thy Children)</hi> which is Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically vſed for the people of <hi>Iudath, Pro ſubditis et Diſcipulis</hi> (as Saint <hi>Hieron</hi>) For the ſubiects vnto the Prince, who is<note n="a" place="margin">Nurcing Fathers, &amp;c. Iſai. 49.23.</note> 
               <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> the Father of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; And for the Diſciples of the Prieſts, who are<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.15. Gal. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes ſpirituales in Chriſto,</hi> The ſpiritual fathers of their Flockes in Chriſt; To both whome, both thoſe are Children.</p>
            <p>Whereout as the care of Superiours ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be collected;<note place="margin">Obedience of inferiours.</note> ſo the obedience and honour which Inferiours owe vnto them, ſhall firſt be obſerued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Neſcit regnare, qui non didicit obedire,</hi> He knowes not how to Rule, who hath not firſt learned to obeye: And a<note n="c" place="margin">Malach. 1.</note> ſonne honoureth his Father, and a ſeruant feares his Lord, if they be then your Fatherss, where is their honour? If they bee your Lords, where is their feare? For euen ſuch children muſt be obedient vnto theſe their Parents in the Lord. <hi>For that is right,</hi> Eph. 6. <hi>Whether it be vnto the King, as to the ſuperiours, or vnto Gouernours, as vnto thoſe who are ſent of him,</hi> 1. Peter, 2.13.14. 1. Whether they bee in the Church, <hi>Eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum reprehenſiones ſicut ignis vrens cauendae ſunt,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ep. ad Trallian.</note> ſayth <hi>Ignatius,</hi> You muſt feare their menaces as a conſuming fire, <hi>Et reuereamini eos tanquam Chriſtum Ieſum, cuius
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17950:11"/>loci cuſtodes; vt et Epiſcopus, patris vniuer ſorum Typus et forma eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Or whether they be in the Common-weale, you muſt needes be ſubiect, <hi>not onely for feare of wrath, but euen for conſcience ſake,</hi> Rom. 13, 5. For otherwiſe <hi>you purchaſe to your ſelues damnation,</hi> Ver. 2.</p>
            <p>How then will thoſe diſobedient Refractory chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in the diuers Dioceſſe of thoſe reuerend Fathers, the Biſhops of this Church of <hi>England,</hi> pleade theyr exemption from conformable obedience; when if<note n="a" place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> may be credited; <hi>Talis polluta eſt conſcientia, et omni infideli deterior,</hi> Their pretended pure tender conſcience is impurely polluted, and their faith worſe then infidelity: For, ſayth the ſame Father, ſpeaking of <hi>Timothy, Lyncus, Anacletus,</hi> and <hi>Cletus,</hi> the Biſhoppes that miniſtred vnto, and ſucceeded Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> and ſo in them, of all that lawfully ſhould obtaine that calling,<note n="b" place="margin">Loc. citat.</note> 
               <hi>Qui his inobediens fuerit, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp; impius omnino fuerit, et Chriſtum improbans, ac eius ordinationem imminuens;</hi> Hee that ſhall be diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto theſe ſpirituall Fathers, he will not ſticke to ſpot himſelfe with any impiety; yea <hi>Atheiſme</hi> it ſelfe, vpon occaſion, whileſt he dares to derogate from his dignity, whom Chriſt hath ſubſtituted to ſupply his owne ſeate in this earthly Conſiſtory. And neuer trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at thoſe fearefull thunderbolts of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which without Repentance muſt needes dart his ſoule into that place where they lye impriſoned, with which this Father ranckes him. And how ſhall hee pardon them for this, when owing Childrens obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they haue forſaken him.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17950:11"/>
            <p> Where will then thoſe rebellious Children<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Tim. 3, 6.</hi> Diceres ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o Paulu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viuam Monachiſini ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figrem pingere. &amp;c. Calu. in loc. Et Paulo ante, Tanta ſpurcities in Clero Papals, quae vel ſuo foetore totum mundum inficit &amp;c.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly crept into too many houſes, and leading Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſimple women laden with ſinnes, and ledde away with diuers luſts; I meane the Romaniſts, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties borne Subiects, but his Aduerſaries ſworne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants; Where then will they appeare? Or what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection can they plead to procure their pardon? when they haue not onely like the ſonnes of <hi>Belial, caſt of the yoake of obedience</hi> with a <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare,</hi> Luc. 29.14. We will not haue this man raigne ouer vs; But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>clothed themſelues in the roabes of rebellion with</hi> a <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite et occidamus,</hi> Luc. 20.14. Come and let vs kill him: And as of one draught of the cuppe of that<note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 17.4.5</note> 
               <hi>whore of Babylon,</hi> had ſuch <hi>Circaean</hi> operation as to tranſforme them all to more then <hi>Catelinarian</hi> Conſpirators. <hi>Cum patent Portae,</hi> when their flight is free enough, (as<note n="c" place="margin">Ocat. <hi>2.</hi> cent Catel.</note> 
               <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſayd of the Confederates with that Italian Traytor) So that they might all enioy the preſence of their hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing holy Father, if they thought him worth the following to the ſeauen-hilde Citie<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc. 17.9</hi> Septem vrbs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta tugis tibi qua praſidet orbe, <hi>1.</hi> Capt tolinus, <hi>2.</hi> Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, <hi>3.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus <hi>4</hi> Exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus. <hi>5.</hi> Celius, <hi>6.</hi> Vamnalis, <hi>7.</hi> Quirmalis.</note>, and but abide there <hi>Relegati,</hi> that ſo this land might be in ſafety; yet they not herewith ſatisfied, but deſiring to<note n="e" place="margin">Duplici no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine punientur Impoſtores a Deo; Et quod ipſi vero non obediant, vel ab ca deſciuerint, et quod alios quoque ſuo involuant errore. Marlarot: in verba.</note> 
               <hi>deceiue as they are deceyued,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13.<note n="f" place="bottom">Math. 12: 43.44.45.</note> 
               <hi>Like that vncleane Spirit in the Goſpell, Return with ſeauen worſe then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues;</hi> Or at the leaſt, ſeauen times worſe then they were: and ſo, yea oftentimes euen in thoſe ſacred aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies,<note n="g" place="bottom">Cic. Orat. <hi>2.</hi> cont. Catel.</note> 
               <hi>Notant &amp; deſignant oculis ad caedem vnum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemque noſtrum;</hi> Nay let me ioyne <hi>vnumquemque ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum:</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17950:12"/>They marking out not onely the Miniſters for <hi>Martyres,</hi> but alſo the Magiſtrates to bee maſſacred: not like ſonnes, but like ſlaughter-men; or if they bee ſonnes, they are like<note n="a" place="margin">2. Reg. 19.37.</note> 
               <hi>Adramelech</hi> and <hi>Scharezer,</hi> which murther their Father at his ſacrifice; whereas, if theyr offence were onely, <hi>Vetitum contingere limen:</hi> To ſet foot on the forbidden ſhoare, if that bleſſed Martyre Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> were firſt conſulted withall, hee would ſurely reſolue them, that euen that was Rebellion; <hi>Cypr. Rogatiano,</hi> Ep. 7. <hi>Qui in eam Patriam vnde extorris factus eſt regreditur, deprehenſus, non iam quaſi Chriſtianus, ſed quaſi nocens perit,</hi> Hee that returnes without licence, into the confines of that Kingdome, from whence the lawes haue baniſht him, if he be apprehended and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to execution, hee dyes not as in caſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but for the cauſe of Rebellion; Not as a Martyr, but as a malefactor, not as a Chriſtian, but as a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weales diſturber. And how ſhall hee pardon them for this? when owing childrens obedience, they haue thus forſaken him?</p>
            <p>But now as the obedience of Inferiours hath beene thus herehence collected,<note place="margin">The care of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours.</note> 
               <hi>Relatiue,</hi> without any wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: So the duty of Superiours is herein propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Poſitiue,</hi> without any peruerting, which is, That what care Parents ought to haue of their children, to <hi>bring them vp in the feare and nurture of the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prouocation to wrath,</hi> Eph. 6.4. <hi>Ne immodica ſaeuitia exaſperent:</hi> Calu. in Loc. Leaſt by too much cruelty they harden their hearts againſt them. The ſame, or as great care ought Miniſters and Magiſtrates to haue of the bodies and ſoules of the people, and ſubiects
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17950:12"/>ſubordinate vnder them: For as <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3.17.22. <hi>Son of man, I haue made thee a watchman ouer the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> &amp;c. As you may reade there at large; and if they miſcarry through thy default, <hi>their bloud ſhall bee requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at thy hands;</hi> For thou canſt not anſwere, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Cain</hi> thought to haue excuſed himſelfe; <hi>Am I my Brothers Keeper?</hi> For behold, like as <hi>Ruben,</hi> Gen. 43.9 <hi>became ſurety for his younger brother Bentamin,</hi> ſo that his father ſhould require him at his hands: So is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery elder Brother, who hath the<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 12.13 14,</note> diuiding of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the Common weale, or the diſtributing of the<note n="b" place="margin">Ibid. v. 42.</note> portion in the Church (that is, Magiſtrates or Miniſters) made ſureties for the yonger<note n="c" place="margin">Gen, 35.18.</note> 
               <hi>Benonies,</hi> or ſonnes of ſorrow, that is, the common people, who are indeed<note n="d" place="margin">Ver. cod.</note> 
               <hi>Beniamins,</hi> the ſonnes of the right hand of ſtrength vnto their Soueraigne: And at their hands will God require them: For if it be iuſt (as moſt iuſt it is) <hi>to viſite the iniquity of the Fathers</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">That doth the like. Ezech. 28.</note> 
               <hi>vpon the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Exod. 20.5. <hi>The tranſgreſſion of the Prince vpon the people,</hi> 2. Sam. 24.10. to 18. Although the child could neyther reforme the Parent, nor<note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>the people reclaime the Prince:</hi> How much more iuſt ſhall it be to require the bloud of the child at the hand of the Parent, and the bloud of the people, at the hands of their <hi>Preſidents</hi> if they periſh through their default.</p>
            <p>And therefore let the Miniſter ſtand vppon his watch, and the Magiſtrate vpon his guard, 1. That the one may know what to anſwere when he is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Neuer comming from his Watch-Tower in the day time, nor from his ward in the night, vntill he ſee the Chariot and Horſemen, which ſhall beate down Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17950:13"/>and breake all the grauen images of her Gods vnto the ground,</hi> Iſai, 21.8.9. 2. And the other may bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> deſcribes him, <hi>A Keeper of the Law by the sword,</hi> Which is commaunded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word: Wherein<note n="a" place="margin">Orat: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Iſocrates</hi> counſell is not to be contemned, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>At my hand take this to heart, that no vniuſt perſon of a corrupt conſcience be vſed as an inſtrument in thine office:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Quid predeſt bonas &amp; vtiles adeſſe Leges, niſi commodus adſit carum taterpres.</note> For what ſhall it profite the Law to bee perfect, and thy intenſion vpright, if the execution bee abuſed by infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. And therefore as the Magiſtrates themſelues<note n="c" place="margin">2. Chron. 19</note> take heede what they doe, knowing that they deale not for man but for the Lord, with whom there is no iniquity: So let the feare of the Lord bee vpon thoſe which miniſter about them, that they reſpect not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; nor take no gifts: For otherwiſe euen Chriſt him ſelfe may be betrayed for a <hi>Quid dabitis,</hi> Mat. 26.15. A League may be concluded with <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon,</hi> by making friends to <hi>Blaſtus,</hi> Act. 12.20. The Temple and Treaſury be turnde ouer to <hi>Apollonius Heliodorus,</hi> or <hi>Iaſon,</hi> for enuie, or an office. 2. <hi>Mach.</hi> 3. and 4. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: yea, all the people may be ſuffred to forſake God; <hi>by him who makes his gold his God,</hi> or by ſuch a<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12, 15.16.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon, as hath like<note n="e" place="margin">Gen 24.30 to 34.</note> 
               <hi>Eſau ſolde his owne Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for a meſſe of pottage: For hee will ſell Gods inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the Lentills that made it: And then how ſhall he pardon thee for this? When thy children,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thy Children, Tui non mei: Hieron:</hi> Thine not mine: So long as they were obedient throughout the paſſage of ſacred Writ; God ſtiles himſelfe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Iſrael, And them my children,</hi> as Deut. 32.6.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17950:13"/>
               <hi>Is not he thy Father that hath bought thee?</hi> And Ier. 31.9 <hi>I am a Father to Iſrael, and Ephraim is my firſt borne, but when multiplying and maintaining ſinne, they became back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders,</hi> then he cals them, <hi>not My, but Thy Children:</hi> And as <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.25. <hi>Through faith he called them his people, which were not his people, and her beloued which was not beloued:</hi> Hoſ. 1.6.9. So through fall hee figures her <hi>Lo-Ruhamah,</hi> and them <hi>Lo-Ammi, to whom hee had beene a God, and they his people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereout we may ſee the immediate,<note place="margin">The effect of Sinne.</note> inſeparable effect of ſinne, which is a forſaking, and being forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of God: For as Gen. 31. to 6. In that firſt offence was a forſaking of Gods commandement, and relying vpon the Serpent; So euery ſinne ſince, is a forſaking. God, and following Sathan: Whereupon 1. Ioh. 3.7 8. <hi>As if they who taught, or thought otherwiſe, were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:</hi> The Apoſtle confirmeth it by this Caution; <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Children let no man deceyue you, he that committeth ſin is of the Diuell, for the Diuell ſinneth</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>not</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Non in nutio, ſed ab nutio, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quia formatus ſuerit a Deo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſed quia ab uſius peccati ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordio. (Quod ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o capit origine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Nam ante illius lapſum non erat peccatum) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icatus eſt Dei legem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſuſque, a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiua bonitate ſua, &amp; decidit in prauitatem, a qua nunquam deſtitit; ſed in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> continue perſtat, ſemper mala malis accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans: Cyril. in Io. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> vbi tractat hac ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba.</note> 
               <hi>from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninning:</hi> Of the <hi>Deuill, Non creatione, ſed corruptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> not by Creation, but by Corruption; <hi>Non Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uè, ſed Priuatiuè,</hi> as the Schoole-men diſtinguiſh it; not by Forming, but by forſaking, as our Prophet phraſeth it: And how iuſt is it then for the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to pronounce againſt ſuch Apoſtatates,<note n="b" place="margin">2. Eſd. 1.25</note> 
               <hi>Derelinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes mederelinqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> They that forſake me, I wil forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 He doth not ſay, <hi>that haue not knowne me;</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Ignorance it ſelfe be not excuſable,</hi> Pſal. 95.10. Eſpecially, <hi>Si modo ſit vincibilis. Pet: Lomb: l.</hi> 2. <hi>ſen: d.</hi> 22. If man might haue got out of it by any indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry which was omitted by him; yea, <hi>In ijys qui non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuerunt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17950:14"/>paena peccati,</hi> As<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Auguſtinr, In thoſe who could not ouercome it, if it ſelfe be not a ſinne, yet is it ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the puniſhment of ſinning.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Neyther doth hee ſay, That haue not beleeued in me, although ſuch <hi>as heare and beleeue not, haue no cloake for their ſinne,</hi> Iohn 15.22. <hi>Neque vt ab omni Damnatione liberarentur, neque vt aliquanto leuius dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narentur,</hi> As Saint <hi>Auguſtine, ſuper Ioh: Tract.</hi> 89. Neyther vrterly to free themſelues from damnation, nor to purchaſe therein ſome degree of mitigation.</item>
               <item>3 But he ſayth, <hi>That haue forſaken mee,</hi> ſignifying, that it is the moſt grieuous ſinne which can ſeaze vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoule of man,<note place="margin">Apoſtaſie.</note> that when God hath vouchſafed him the gracious calling of his ſacred Spirit:<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 9.62.</note> He then takes his hand from the <hi>Plough,</hi> &amp; looking backe, makes himſelfe vnfit for the Kingdome of Heauen: For, as Saint<note n="c" place="margin">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ern. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, That <hi>Tribus gradibus ad Pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum peruenitur, ſuggeſtione Delectatione, Conſenſione,</hi> We come to ſinnes ſecret Chamber by three ſtayres, Suggeſtion, Delight and Conſent: and as<note n="d" place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> de Sum. <hi>60.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi> Apud Lomb.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſidore</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth ſinnes into a Tripartite order: Of <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Infirmity</hi> and <hi>Induſtry,</hi> Making thoſe of Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity greater then thoſe of Ignorance, and thoſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, greater then thoſe of Infirmity; So may I not vnaptly alter them in matters of Religion,<note n="e" place="margin">Vnde Paulus inſi nem earn defeitunem quae Antiduſts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pracedet. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>2.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>2.3.</hi> ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dent in</note> into ſins of Ignorance, Infidelity and Apoſtaſie: wherein how much Infidelity exceedeth Ignorance, ſo much Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie ſurpaſſeth Infidelity: for it had beene better ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue knowne the way of righteouſneſſe, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue knowne it, to turne from the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement deliuered to them, like the <hi>Dogge to his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17950:14"/>vomit, and the Sow to her Mire,</hi> 2. Pet. 2.21.22. It being almoſt impoſſible for them who were once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and had taſted of the heauenly gift, and were made partakers of the holy Ghoſt, and had taſted of the good Word of God, and the powers of the world to come, <hi>That they falling away</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Vide Deering on the Heb. &amp;c. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Deniſon Sermen at Paules Croſſe.</note> (.i.) 1. <hi>Wittingly,</hi> 2. <hi>Willingly,</hi> 3. <hi>Malitiouſly,</hi> and 4. <hi>Totally,</hi> that they ſhould be renued againe by repentance, Heb. 6.4.5.6. And without that <hi>there is no Pardon,</hi> Luc. 13.3. Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed Brethren, leſt there bee in any of you an euill heart of vnbeleefe in departing from the liuing God; <hi>But exhort one another dayly whileſt it is called to day, leaſt any of you bee hardned through the deceitfulneſſe of Sinne,</hi> Heb. 3.12.13. And ſo at the length you heare this reaſon, as a Counterplea againſt your pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Thy Children haue for ſaken me,</hi> &amp;c. And thus much of the firſt part, and firſt particle of the ſecond part, of the Reaſon which is the perſons, and their Apoſtaſie. Now to the ſecond, which is the enſuing ſinnes: <hi>And ſworne by thoſe that be no Gods,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt of Swearing; <hi>And ſworne,</hi> Wherein, that we might at once meete with the impiety of the Papiſt, the prophaneſſe of the Atheiſt, and the errour of the Anabaptiſt; We will briefly runne through thoſe <hi>Sweares.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Firſt, What an Oath is?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Secondly, Whether it be lawfull to ſweare at all, or not?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Thirdly, When it is lawfull?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Fourthly, How we muſt ſweare?</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17950:15"/>
               <item>5 <hi>What is to be auoyded in Swearing?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>Sixthly, What is the puniſhment of offenders by Swearing?</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>For the Firſt,<note place="margin">An Oath.</note> 
               <hi>Perkins</hi> our Engliſh Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>Caſ: Conſ: Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>ſ.</hi> 1, hath left vs this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>An Oath is a religious and neceſſary confirmation of things doubtfull, by calling on God to be a witneſſe of the truth, and a Reuenger of falſhood.</hi> 1. A Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to that of the Apoſtle, Heb. 6.16. An oath for Confirmation, is amongſt men the ende of ſtrife, 2 And that a religious, not a prophane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, anſwerable to that of the Prophet, Iſai, 19.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſweare by the Lord of Hoſtes</hi> (.i.) as part of thy Religion, that thou ſweare by none other. 3, And <hi>that onely neceſſary, and not needleſſe,</hi> Math. 5.34.4. And that alwayes truely and not treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly: For <hi>God will come neere to ſuch in iudgement, and be a ſwift witnes againſt them,</hi> Mal. 3.5.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, ſithence an oath is a Confirmation and end of ſtrife, the reuerenteſt league betwixt man and man, as appeares in <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Abimelech,</hi> Gen. 26.28.29. <hi>Let there bee an Oath betwixt vs, and let vs make a Couenant with thee, that thou wilt doe vs no hurt: Yea the moſt ſacred bonde betwixt God and man,</hi> Heb. 6.13. When God made promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe he had no greater aſſurance then an Oath to gine him; Nor no greater then himſelfe to ſweare by, <hi>Hee ſwore by himſelfe.</hi> 1. As this dooth admoniſh vs, how inuiolably it ſhould be obſerued. 2. So dooth it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vs how Charily it ſhould be taken.</p>
            <p>As concerning the awfull obſeruing of it, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17950:15"/>antiquity neuer made queſtion,<note place="margin">Reuerence of an Oath, by 1 Beleeners.</note> but it ſurpaſſed the power of all Obligations; Whereupon <hi>Gen.</hi> 24 2. to 10. <hi>Abraham</hi> being to oblige his ſeruant moſt ſurely to performe the greateſt truſt that euer was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, euen for the earthly weale or woe of his<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 22.2, 2 Infidels.</note> 
               <hi>onely ſonne,</hi> hee preferres an Oath before all promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, threates, or pledges, yea euen amongeſt<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Homer. Odyſ. E.</note> 
               <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Idolaters,</hi> it was held ſo ſacred, that <hi>Ahab</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Oath of any Nation, aboue his owne diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Inquiſition, in his perſonall enquirie after <hi>Eliah,</hi> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.10. Yea both amongſt Beleeuers and Infidels it was eſteemed ſo abſolute, as that vpon an Oth,<note n="c" place="margin">Gc. 31.44. to 54</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> truſtes <hi>Laban,</hi> and <hi>Laban Iacob;</hi> Although not onely they differd in the manner of ſeruice, but euen for the Matter ſerued different Gods: The one the Idols, the other, the God of his Fathers: And how religiouſly then ſhould this ſacred Ceremony bee obſerued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, that they might neuer diſappoint their Neighbours of that they ſware vnto them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>it were to their own hinderance,</hi> Pſal. 15.5. And how much more immutably ſhould it binde them to the performance of ſo lawfully confirmed promiſes, beyond all humane Articles, or couenants: Since we doe not ſweare by him that is no God, but by him,<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 20.7</note> 
               <hi>Who will not ſuffer thoſe to goe vnpuniſht, who take his Name in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſince it is ſo: How wary ſhould we bee in entring into ſuch a bond, correſpondent to the Counſell of the Preacher, Eccleſ. 5.2. <hi>Bee not raſhe with thy mouth, and let not thine heart be haſty to vtter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Oath or Vow before God: Suffer not thy mouth to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17950:16"/>cauſe thy ſoule to ſinne, Neyther ſay thou before the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, that it was thine errour: Wherefore ſhould. God bee angry at thy raſh voice, and deſtroy the worke of thine hands,</hi> Ver. 6. Which that we might auoyde, it is not impertinent to conſider.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, whether it be lawfull to ſweare at all or not;<note place="margin">The Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of an oath.</note> When <hi>Mat,</hi> 5.34. and <hi>Iae.</hi> 5.12. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour and his Diſciples direct vs not to ſweare at all? To which the <hi>Geneuiſts</hi> Gloſſe may ſerue for ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent anſwere; That by thoſe wordes, all ſuperfluous Others are vtterly debarred; whether the name of God be therein mentioned, or otherwiſe; But by this hee takes not from the Magiſtrate his Authority; who may require an oath, for the maintenance of Iuſtice, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and trueth: For theſe wordes are to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, like vnto thoſe, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.23.24. <hi>How hardly ſhall a rich man enter into the Kingdome of Heauen,</hi> that is, which truſteth in Riches: So ſweare not at all (that is) in your ordinary communication; <hi>Ne ſcilicet iura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ad facilitatem iurandi veniatur, et de facilitate ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuctudinem, de conſuetudine in Periurium decidatur</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) Leaſt ſwearing grow to facility, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility to cuſtome, cuſtome to habite, habite to periury; <hi>Non penitus iurare probibuit: ſed occaſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perturij (quod perfectius eſt) euitare docuit,)</hi> ſayth <hi>Gregory</hi>) He did not forbidde all lawfull Oathes in a Chriſtian Communal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but that which is more laudable, he taught how to auoyde <hi>Periury:</hi> Whereby the<note n="a" place="margin">Hareſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ata, ex Tradition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>: Clement Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>7.</hi> Vbi diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utat ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bereu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ar, &amp;, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> non pole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u, nec cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> San lis. &amp;c</note> Anabaptiſticall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is confuted, who imagine it vnlawfull to ſweare iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially, which one abſurdity being granted, all ſinne might be protected, and no way for diſcouery: All
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17950:16"/>Truth concealed, and no meanes for enquiry, which <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.10.11. <hi>The Lord appointed ſhould be done by an Oath.</hi> But omitting this becauſe I feare there are more which abuſe it too ordinarily, then there are, which will not vſe it at all.</p>
            <p>I deſcend to the third queſtion, which is, <hi>When an Oath is lawfull?</hi> Which euen the Catechiſticall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples will reſolue to bee at any of theſe three times; 1. When the glory of God is ſought: 2. Or the good of our Brethren, 3. Or before a Magiſtrate, 1 <hi>In Truth,</hi> 2. <hi>in iudgement,</hi> and in 3. <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> Ier. 4.2. For theſe are thoſe <hi>Comites iuramenti,</hi> as<note n="a" place="margin">2 da. 2 dae part. 1. Qu. 89.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> calls them as indiuiſible from a true lawfull oth, as a voice from ſpeech, a ſound from a voyce, or ayre from a ſound; Which that they might bee perpetually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in our Oathes, We muſt be circumſpect,<note place="margin">The Cautions for Oathe.</note> that we onely ſweare, 1. Firſt, <hi>in rebus veris,</hi> Appertaining to true things: Secondly, 2. <hi>Certis,</hi> Vndoubted in our owne knowledge. Thirdly. 3. <hi>Licitis,</hi> Lawfull to bee performed: Fourthly, 4. <hi>Poſſibilibus,</hi> poſſible to be accompliſhed; Fiftly, 5. <hi>Neceſſariis,</hi> Neceſſarie touching, which wee ſhould bee ſo informed: And Sixthly, 6. <hi>Granibus,</hi> weighty &amp; worthy to be ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. <hi>Non vacat exiguis rebus adeſſe Ioui,</hi> GOD may not be called to witneſſe vpon every idle occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſt hee turne a Reuenger of mans preſumption; Which, would it were equally pondered of the ruder Multitude, and riotous <hi>Magnificoes:</hi> 1. Who as the one ſort is accuſtomed <hi>Os ſuum in caelum ponere,</hi> Pſal. 73.8.9. <hi>To ſtretch foorth their mouth againſt Heauen, Whileſt their ſwearing tongues thunder through the world:</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:17950:17"/>So that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tremble at their talking againſt the moſt high, except it be thoſe who are corrupted with their wicked blaſphemy. 2. So the other ſuppoſe it lawfull to ſweare, ſo long as they performe it, which indeede oft times they will doe, were it<note n="a" place="margin">Mark. 6.24.</note> 
               <hi>With Herod, to cut off Iohn Baptiſts head,</hi> Or with<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 23.12</note> 
               <hi>the Iewes to murther Paul:</hi> I would, I ſay the obſeruation of <hi>Saint Ambroſe</hi> might enforme the one,<note n="c" place="margin">Amb. offic. c. 1</note> that <hi>Eſt contra officium, nonnunquam promiſſum ſoluere ſacramentum:</hi> It is oftentimes a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breach of Chriſtian duety to performe that Oath, which a man vowes raſhly: It being a ſinne to make it, and a greater not to breake it: And the example of <hi>Nicanor</hi> might reforme the other, <hi>Whoſe blaſphemous tong the ſame day it offended was cut out of his head, and caſt to the Fowles of the ayre,</hi> 2. Macha. 15.33. That ſo they might feare to accuſtome their mouthes to ſwearing, or to vſe themſelues to the naming of the holy one; For as a ſeruant that is continually beaten, ſhal not be without a blew marke: So hee that ſweareth, and nameth God continually, ſhall not bee faultleſſe. A man that vſeth much ſwearing, ſhall bee filled with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, and the plague ſhall neuer depart from his houſe, if hee offend, his ſinne ſhall bee vpon him, and if he acknowledge not his ſinne, hee commits a double offence, and if hee ſweare in vaine, hee ſhall not bee innocent; but his houſe ſhall bee full of Calamities: There is a Word that is cloathed about with death: God graunt that it bee not found in <hi>the Heritage of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> for all ſuch thinges ſhall bee farre from the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and they ſhall not wallow in their ſinnes. <hi>Vſe not thy mouth then to vntemperate ſwearing, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17950:17"/>is that word of ſinne,</hi> Eccleſ. 23.9. to 13. And what canſt thou ſay, <hi>Why God ſhould pardon thee for this?</hi> Since therein worſe then <hi>Nicanor,</hi> thou blaſphemeſt him: for hee knew not GOD, but <hi>Thou haſt forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him, and ſworne by thoſe that he no Gods,</hi> or elſe by him as if he were no God.</p>
            <p>Since therefore, although an Oath bee lawfull. yet it is lyable to ſo many Cautions, as that onely, 1. <hi>Piety,</hi> 2. <hi>Charity,</hi> or 3. <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> muſt exact it. Herein is context and wouen.</p>
            <p>The fourth Queſtion:<note place="margin">The manner of taking an Oath.</note> How we muſt take an oath when wee doe ſweare? And that muſt bee plainely without inuerting others words or vnderſtanding; Or equiuocating in our owne intenſions. 1. Firſt, <hi>Plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> If they bee witneſſes betwixt <hi>Plea</hi> and <hi>Plea,</hi> for Life or goods, according to his iutenſion of whoſe words or doings they giue Teſtimonie; and not according to their owne peruerſe expoſition of them: Like thoſe falſe witneſſes againſt our Sauiour, who applyed that ſpeech which he vttered touching his <hi>Body, Ioh.</hi> 2.19. as au occaſion to accuſe him for an enemy to the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Math. 26.61.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, <hi>Plainely;</hi> If they be parties vpon whom <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 17.18.19</note> 
               <hi>Lot is fallen, to giue glory to God,</hi> that they<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe plainely, and denie not, according to the common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of him which adminiſtreth the Oth vnto them;</hi> For as <hi>Iſiod: de ſum: bo: l.</hi> 1. <hi>Quacunque arte verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quis iuret, Deus tamen qui Conſcientiae teſtis, eſt ita boc accipit, ſicut ille cui iuratur intelligit:</hi> With what
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17950:18"/>ſoeuer arte of wordes a man endeauour to delude in ſwearing God who is the witneſſe of the heart dooth ſo accept it, as hee who is the Miniſter in giuing the oath doth vnderſtand it; and therefore muſt <hi>euery one ſpeake the truth from his heart, yea though it bee to his hinderance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then will our Ieſuited<note n="a" place="margin">Artius bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demanded to ſubſcribe, &amp; alſo vrged to an oath for Confirmation of his ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, did both, Swearing that he beleeued, as he had written, when indeed he had written his owne op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on in a Paper, which he carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnder his arme, when he layde his hand vpon the booke, and ſo ſome now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qiruocate, but whether Papiſt or Puritane, for ſuch will equiuocate alſo Let them take heed and feare Atrius his end, Socrat, Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt. Hiſt. l. 1. c. 25. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty.</note> Arrian Equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors excuſe themſelues, for their euaſions and reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with <hi>Lingua iuraui mentem iniuratam gero,</hi> If wee appeale but to the Fathers, on whoſe ſhoulders they boaſt, that theyr Religion leaneth: Surely, they muſt ſend vs another <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> or a new ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of Cenſuraes, vpon their ſpurious paſſages, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Elench</hi> of their errours, or elſe how will they bee pardoned for this? when not onely they forſake him, <hi>and ſweare by thoſe that are no Gods,</hi> but alſo they blaſpheme his Name, foreſwearing by him that is the true God.</p>
            <p>Out of that which hath already beene deliuered, it is not vneaſie to coniecture, what contraries are to bee auoyded.</p>
            <p>Of which</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt is ſwearing falſely, <hi>Leu.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſweare by my name falſely;</hi> For behold a <hi>flying Booke is gone foorth vpon the Earth, and it ſhall enter into the Houſe of him that ſweares falſely by my Name, as well as of him that ſteales, and it ſhall remayne in the middeſt of his Houſe, and ſhall conſume it With the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof, and with the ſtones thereof,</hi> ſayeth the Lord, <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.1. to 5. And that worthily; for whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt man by Fore-ſwearing cals God to teſtifie an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17950:18"/>What doth hee elſe but ſay in his heart, <hi>Tuſhe, thou God careſt not for it,</hi> Pſal. 11.11. <hi>But thou wilt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iuſtifie miſchiefe and wrong, ver.</hi> 14. And what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter blaſphemie can there bee againſt the Deitie, Or what more to bee auoyded?</p>
            <p>Which that we may take heed of, 2. We muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily ſhunne ſwearing familiarly; For as <hi>Chryſeſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſual ſwearing</note> 
               <hi>ſuper Math.</hi> 5. <hi>Nemo eſt qui frequenter iuret, qni aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do non periuret,</hi> Looke how in many wordes there will bee folly: So in many oathes will follow periury: And therefore attend to the Iniunction of the Almighty,<note place="margin">Swearing by Creatures.</note> touching this particular So often as thou heareſt, or vttereſt his name, <hi>thou ſhalt feare this glorious and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full name, the Lord thy God,</hi> Deut. 28.18. So that as <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. <hi>At the Name of Ieſus euery knee ſhall bow,</hi> Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaby, at the name of <hi>Iehouah</hi> euery hart ſhall tremble, and not dare to vſe it familiarlie: For ſuch fall to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it falſely. <hi>And then how ſhall hee pardon them for this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor are they to ſuppoſe that they can ſhift the guilt of this ſinne, by ſwearing fondly, as by creatures, or ſuperſtitiouſly as by Idols. Let<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> dae. <hi>2</hi> dae. part. <hi>1.</hi> Q. <hi>89.</hi> Loc. Citat.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> and the other Schoolemen herein follow their fantaſies, I am not for them, Neyther <hi>Quoad</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Simplex Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatio innitur diuinae veritati ſicut &amp; ſides, &amp;c. Exceratione vero indueitur Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, &amp;c. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Conteſtationem,</hi> Nor <hi>Quoad Execrationem,</hi> Neyther <hi>In quantum diuina veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas manifeſtatur in Creaturis;</hi> Nor, <hi>In quantum Diuinum Iudicium exercetur in Creatura.</hi> As they diſtinguiſh: For<note n="c" place="margin">Perk. Golden Chaine, c. 22 As Pledges &amp; Cognizances of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp;c. 1, Cor. 15.31 1. Sam. 20, 3. As the Lord liueth, and as thy ſoule li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Homer Odyſ.</note> howſoeuer in aſſeuerations the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures may bee vſed, yet in oathes, They as well as Idolls are abſolutely to bee eſchewed; for as the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty with great circumſpection interdicts the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17950:19"/>that they ſhould not make mention of the names of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods, <hi>Neyther let them be heard out of their mouth,</hi> Exod. 23.13. So our Sauiour expreſly prohibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>the ſwearing by any Creature,</hi> Mat. 5.35.36.<note n="a" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le D. Hylar. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>12</hi> paulo a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio ſuper his verbis.</note> Leſt thereby they ſhould ſeeme <hi>To worſhippe and Jerue the creature more then the Creator, who is bleſſed for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> Rom. 1, 25. For what dooth man elſe whileſt hee ſweares by them, but attribute Omniſcience and Omnipotency to them, which are peculiar onely to God. And therefore as <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. &amp; 10.20. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy God, and ſerue him, and to him ſhalt thou cleaue, and ſweare onely by his Name, &amp; not by thoſe that are no Gods:</hi> For otherwiſe in ſteade of taking his name in vaine, by ſwearing by the true God, thou committeſt Idolatry, by ſwearing by thoſe that are no Gods.</p>
            <p>How then can the Papiſts, who maintaine &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the ſwearing by Creatures, as the <hi>Bleſſed Lady, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> departed; Yea (that which is more) by thoſe which eyther are, or were no Creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their owne ſuperſtition made them Idols; How can they, I ſay, excuſe themſelues from being guilty of this ſinne? Or what is it poſſible they ſhould plead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for their pardons, Who <hi>haue thus forſaken him, and ſworne by thoſe that are no Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the Caſe bee ſo hard to procure a pardon; then me thinkes I heare ſome ſcoffer ſay, Wee would know the puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Which is the laſt Circumſtance conſiderable in this ſinne,<note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c.</note> as in all others, For ſo in ſin, ſtill puniſhment makes the period.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17950:19"/>
            <p> To whom I returne this Reſolution, Beſides, <hi>that the Wages of euery ſinne is death,</hi> Rom. 6.23. Both <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae &amp; Corporis,</hi> Temporall and Eternall, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently may be concluded of this, There are many great and grieuous puniſhments, both priuate and publike, which eſpecially attende vpon this ſinne of 1. Swearing 2. For-ſwearing, and 3. Idolatrous ſwearing Fondly by thoſe that are no Gods.</p>
            <p>For as the Pſalmiſt ſayth expreſly, <hi>The mouthes of thoſe that ſweare by falſe Gods ſhall be ſtopped, and confounded ſhall they be that worſhip them that are no Gods;</hi> So vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly wil he haue their names taken out of our mouths, <hi>as that there may be no more remembrance of them,</hi> Hoſ. 2.16.17.—And<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.1, 23. Swearing is ranckt in the prime place of thoſe ſinnes, for which the Lorde enters ſuch a controuerſie with the Land, <hi>That the whole ſhall mourne for it, and euery particular inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant that dwelleth therein ſhall languiſh, with the very beaſtes of the Fields, and the Foules of heauen, yea the fiſhes of the ſea.</hi> And I pray God it be now no occaſion, that the creatures growne ſo vnder, yea ſuffer ſo for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And as for forſwearing, Not onely the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar puniſhment of <hi>Zidkiiah,</hi> may ſhew how hatefull it is, and how rigorouſly reuenged; who was himſelfe taken Captiue, and ſaw his ſonnes ſlaine before his face; and laſtly, had his eyes put out, and <hi>being bounde in Fetters of Braſſe, was</hi> (though a King) <hi>carried priſoner to Babylon,</hi> 2. Reg. 25.6.7. becauſe hee forſware him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and brake that oath (in his owne perſon) which <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> had cauſed him to ſweare by GOD,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17950:20"/>2. <hi>Chr.</hi> 36.23. But the puniſhment of Periury, euen vpon the poſteritie of thoſe who durſt to violate their Forefathers vowes, may more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manifeſt to any who will vnderſtand the ſeuere indignation of him, whoſe name is blaſphemed by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three yeares fearefull famine ouerrunnes al Iſrael,</hi> 2. Sam. 21.1. vntill <hi>ſeauen ſonnes of Saul are hanged vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sunne,</hi> Ver. 6. for breaking but one Oath, and that none of his owne,<note n="a" place="margin">Ioſh. 9 13.19.20.</note> but made three hundred yeares before by <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ver. 14, 22 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yea and that procured by fraud too; So Religious ſhould the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of an Oath be, (euen to deceyuers) And ſo great is the Diuine reuenge vpon the violaters, euen in poſterity.</p>
            <p>Nor is it onely of this obliging efficacy, if it be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by ſuch parties, as are both ſeruants of the true God; but euen betwixt Beleeuers and Inſidels, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Mahumetans, Iewes or Pagans: As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the afore cited approuing practiſes of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ahimelech, Iacob</hi> and <hi>Laban,</hi> doe ſufficiently proue it, appeares moſt euidently in the ſucceſſe of<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſinus apud B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>le,</hi> Theater of Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> 
               <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> K. of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> who breaking that league with <hi>Amurath</hi> the Turke, of which there were Articles engroſſed in both Languages, and a ſolemne Oath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for confirmation on both parties, &amp; by means of that perfidious truce-breaking, the Hungarians at firſt hauing the vpper hand; No ſooner <hi>Amurath</hi> (although almoſt ouercome) pulled out of his boſome the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the violated Truce, and lifting vp his eyes to Heauen, vttered theſe ſpeeches; <hi>O Ieſu Chriſt, theſe are the Leagues that thy Chriſtians haue made and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17950:20"/>by ſwearing by thy Name, and yet haue broken them againe; If thou beeſt a God as they ſay thou art, Reuenge this iniury which is offered both thee and me, &amp; puniſh thoſe Truce-breaking Varlets.</hi> No ſooner, I ſay, had <hi>Amurath</hi> vttered thoſe wordes, but the Chriſtians Battell and courage began to rebate; <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> him ſelfe was ſlaine by the <hi>Ianizaries,</hi> his whole Army diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited, and all his people put to the ſword, ſauing a few that fledde; So powerfully ſhould an oath bind; or ſo apparantly wil the Lord puniſh Periury, although it were to the prophaneſt perſons.</p>
            <p>The Pope then muſt ſend for another <hi>Iulian</hi> to his Legate (<note n="a" place="margin">D. Bearde, vbi ſupra.</note> for it was he that brake the foreſaid League, and he had need be <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata too) to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Poſition; That <hi>Haereticis fides non eſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanda,</hi> oathes are not to bee kept with Heretikes: for that abſurd Blaſphemie being granted, what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury may not be patronized? yea what<note n="b" place="margin">Ita vt Reges l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dint Paclis, &amp; iuramentis ſicut Puers aſtraga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ludere ſolent, vt olim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on ſuit in Apotheg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate &amp; vt nue Pontificia conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liabula Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themat is, &amp;c. Chemmi: Exam: Conc. Trid. part. <hi>2</hi> Can. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> Alterations in Religion, vpon a States aduantage, might not bee abetted? or what condemning the Orthodoxe for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes in a Conclaue of Cardinals, to the violating a Lay-League for hoſtile policie, or infringing an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ſafe Conduct for <hi>Andraduis</hi> aduantage, in a Tridentine Aſſembly may not be maintained? yea what Priuate ſpirited Periurer could euer bee conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceel, if hee would (as wee haue indifferent experience that they will) but hold others to be Heretikes? Vpon this ground <hi>Galeaceus</hi> may haue as many wiues as <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Gallinaceus,</hi> if hee can but accuſe his former of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: That I may omit, becauſe it hath beene
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17950:21"/>often inſiſted vpon; how a Subiect may diſpence with his allegiance to his Soueraigne, if hee diſſent from him in Religion; But O good God, what ſafety for Princes? what ſecurity for States? What peace for the publike? what Piety for the Priuate? could euer be expected prouided, or preſerued? If the infectious aire <hi>of theſe</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 16.13 14.</note> 
               <hi>vnclean Spirits, which thus come out of the mouth of the Dragon, the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet,</hi> againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Kings and States ſhould bee ſuffered to ſet the World at battell, againſt the great day of GOD Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty? <hi>How ſhould hee pardon thee for this? If thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould ſo forſake him, and not onely ſweare,</hi> but alſo forſweare <hi>by theſe that are no Gods?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as they thus forſake him and his precepts: So we forſake them and their Poſitions; and proſecute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe other and their practiſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who when hee fedde them to the full, they by troupes haunted Harlots Houſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Ingratitude &amp; Plenty.</note> 
               <hi>When I fedde them to the full:</hi> Whereout appeares their great ingratitude; Nor is it their caſe alone, but incident almoſt to all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> to be then moſt faulty, when God is moſt fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; So<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 49.20.</note> fooliſh is man that Proſperity ſlayes him'<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 119.67.</note> whom miſery makes remember God (as the Pſalmiſt long ſince obſerued) When <hi>Ieſurun was fatte hee kic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the heele, and when hee was growne thicke, and couered with fleſh, then hee forſooke God that made him, and lightly eſteemed the Rocke of his Saluation,</hi> Deut. 32.14. And <hi>take heed,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 16.19</note> 
               <hi>O yee that are clothed in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17950:21"/>and fine Linnen, and fare delitiouſly euery day,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 144.12.13.</note> whoſe <hi>ſonnes grow vp as the young plants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luxuriae Currus quaderga volui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>um, Ingluuie vent, is libidme cottus, veſtium mollute oly ſoporiſque reſolutione Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hitur equis duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus proſperitate vitae, &amp; re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um abundantta: Bern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Cant:</note> 
               <hi>and your daughters as the poliſhed Corners of the Temple, whoſe Garners bee full and plenteous with all maner of ſtore, and whoſe ſheepe bring foorth thouſands and tenne thouſands,</hi> or whoſe<note n="b" place="margin">1. Reg. 10.11.15.27.</note> 
               <hi>Ships bring home ſpices, Almuggin trees, and golde of Ophir in ſuch plenty, that you haue Cedars like the Sica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiore, and ſiluer like the ſtones. Take heede (I ſay) that you</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 106.13 19.</note> 
               <hi>forget not God, or lightly eſteeme his counſell, ſo that Luſt ſhould come vpon you, That neyther you, nor thoſe about you, take not</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ezech. 16.17 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>your fayre Iewels of gold and of ſiluer, your broydered garments, flowre, Oyle, and Incenſe, your meat and hony wherewith hee ſedde you, to commit whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſpirituall or corporall by them, leaſt God giue you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your enemtes hand, to throw downe your eminent places, and breake downe your high places, and ſtrippe you of your cloathes, and ſpoyle you of your fayre Iewels, and leaue you naked and bare,</hi> Ezech. 16.39. <hi>For how ſhould hee pardon thee for this? if thou forſake him, and ſweare by thoſe that are no Gods. And when hee hath fedde thee to the ful, thou then committeſt adultery, and by troupes haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Harlots Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is the vgly Iſſue of that deformed Impe Ingratitude, monſtrouſly brought foorth againſt the courſe of Nature of ſo fayre a mother, as Plentie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When I fedde thee to the full, thou then committedſt adultery, and by Troupes baunteſt Harlots Houſes:</hi> Which that I might not palliate,<note place="margin">Adultery and vncleanneſſe.</note> I will not onely reſtraine it to that Capitall Colonell of the crime, which <hi>Mars</hi>-like marcheth, <hi>Ad alterius Thorum,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17950:22"/>to wit Adultery; but as the ſinne is large, ſo will I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the vnderſtanding, euen ſo farre as <hi>the bitter root of Concupiſeence.</hi> Mat. 5.28. From whence it hath the beginning: for as the groſſe ſinne is ſo to bee ſhunde, as that it ought not once to bee named amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.3. So are the moſt ſpecious<note n="a" place="margin">Quis eius mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiplices ſpecies enumerare vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at Hac Pentapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin cum adaac n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Regione ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertit, Syenem cum populo inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remit: Filios Iudae pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cuſsit, Iudaeum &amp; Madia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>item pugione tranſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, Tribum Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin deleuit; filios H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrauit, Vriant occidit, Ammon interſecit, Ruben maledixit, Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonem ſeducit, Salamontem peruertit, &amp;c. Hug.</note> 
               <hi>Species</hi> ſo pernitious, <hi>That it is a ſhame euen to ſpeake thoſe thinges which are done of them in priuate,</hi> Eph. 5.12. They bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt thoſe extreames, <hi>Quae carent nominibus,</hi> which want Names bad enough to their Nature, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> ſpeakes of ſome vices, or almoſt allied to thoſe nefarious offences, againſt which <hi>Lycurgus</hi> aueares the making of no Lawes; leaſt man ſhould thereby learne that which before he looked not after: And therefore to auoyde infecting ſome fayrer Plants, whileſt wee ſhould anotomize ſo many filthy haunts, as ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer all the skirts of this ſinne. We will onely a far off, as through a Perſpectiue or Opticke Inſtrument, ſuruey theſe three Deformities in this den of <hi>Cacus,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Firſt, the generall vnlawfulneſſe of it.</item>
                  <item>2 Secondly, certaine particulars to bee eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed of thoſe, who would not fall by it.</item>
                  <item>3 Thirdly, the puniſhments of Offenders in it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The vnlawfulneſſe of it is offered to our view, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as in that ſhort Law of the Decalogue; Ten words (as ſom ſtile them) or commandements of God; One of them is,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod, 20.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery,</hi> yea, and that before the Prohibition of Theft, ſignifying
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17950:22"/>that it is more haynous before God, &amp; hateful to man, then <hi>ſtealing:</hi> for men doe not deſpiſe a Theefe, if hee ſteale to ſatisfie his ſoule when it is hungry: but if he be found, hee ſhall reſtore ſeuen-fold, or he ſhall giue all the ſubſtance of his houſe: But who ſo committeth Adultery with a Woman, lacketh vnderſtanding: Hee that doeth it deſtroyeth his owne ſoule, A Wound and diſhonour ſhall hee get, and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach ſhall not bee wiped away: For Iealouſie is the rage of a man, therefore hee will not ſpare in the day of Vengeance: He will not regard any ranſome, neyther will hee bee content though thou giueſt many giftes. <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.30. to 35. But becauſe this was ſpoken in the time of the Law, <hi>when Adultery was Death,</hi> Leuiticus 20.10. Leaſt ſome licentious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine nourced amongſt the Nicolaitanes, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> an l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Achamoth</hi> of the Gnoſtickes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending himſelfe to bee <hi>Naturaliter ſpiritualis,</hi> And yet will giue <hi>Carnalia Carnalibus,</hi> as <hi>Ireneus</hi> obſerues of them, ſhould dreame of a diſpenſation for this ſinne vnder the Goſpell, becauſe <hi>Chriſt ſeemes to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the ſeuerity of the ſentence,</hi> Iohn 8.2. to 10. There was an eſpeciall care<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 15.29.</note> at the firſt Councell of the Apoſtles, to enioyne Abſtinence from Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That as<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 23.17</note> no Whore might be found amongeſt the Daughters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo<note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.9.10. Heb. 12.16.</note> no Whoremonger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſonnes of <hi>Emanuel,</hi> Whereupon <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19 20 21. The Apoſtle placeth Adultery, Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Vncleanneſſe, and Laſciuiouſneſſe; before Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Witch-craft, Hatred, Variance, Emulation, Wrath, ſtrife, and Sedition:<note n="e" place="margin">Vel ideo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit alijs operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus caernis. quia ad hac caro ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis prochuis eſt Marlorat.</note> as if it were more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17950:23"/>then any of the other, and that not vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.<note n="a" place="margin">Hae ommaſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentu eſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ad Luxuria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lyra.</note> It indeed oftentimes producing all the other: If thou wilt ſee Adultery beget Idolatry, thou needeſt but caſt an eye on<note n="b" place="margin">Reg. 11.1. to 9.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon;</hi> If Witchcraft, reflect on<note n="c" place="margin">2. Reg. 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>Iezabel:</hi> If thou wilt behold Luſt in Trauell with Hatred and Reuenge;<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 39.20.</note> 
               <hi>Putiphars</hi> Wife is at full time of Deliuery; And if thou dareſt endure to ſee Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hatcht out of it, becauſe<note n="e" place="margin">Mark. 6.17 to 29.</note> 
               <hi>Herods</hi> is not high en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, bring on a ſtranger (although a Prophet)<note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.1. to 30.</note> 
               <hi>Amon</hi> and <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſhall bring it to light, euen amongeſt Brethren: Wherefore, except a man will open the ſluce for all ſinnes to flow with a full current, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute himſelfe to the vaſſalage of euery vice without reſiſtance, he may palpably perceyue the vnſufferable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this ſinne, which as that <hi>Dragon,</hi> Apoc. 12.4. <hi>Drawes downe the third part of the Starres of Heauen with his Tayle:</hi> Or as <hi>Sampſons Foxes,</hi> Iudges 15.4.5. <hi>Coupled by Firebrandes in theyr tailes, burnt the Philtſtines Corne vpon the Earth:</hi> So this Tayle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tying ſinne extinguiſheth the greater parte of the Vertues and Faculties of the Soule, which ſhould ſhine like the Starres for light and direction in mans Heauenly halfe: And ſchorcheth, dryeth vppe and conſumeth the Radicall moyſture, ſtrength and vigor of the Body, which ſhould flouriſh like the corne for maintenance and ſuſtentation in mans earthly halfe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſithence that although the Holy Ghoſt aggrauates this ſinne aboue all other, as bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="a" place="margin">Non ſolum maculat animain ſed faedat perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam: Omne namque pectatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo. leunque ſecerit home ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra corpus ſuum eſt qui autem formicatur in corpus ſuum peceat; Semper allam praecedit Ardor &amp; Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulantia ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per comitatur, Foetor &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund tiae. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g.</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17950:23"/>within the Body, whereas others are without; 1. Cor. 6.15. Yet<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 7 51.</note> Stiffe-necked man, who alwayes reſiſts the ſacred Spirit, endeuours to extenuate it, as beeing moſt Naturall to the body and inherent; which indeed is too true as all Diuines determine, that<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 7 51.</note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net fomes et Concupiſcentia,</hi> euen <hi>in Renatis,</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it bee ſoone extinguiſht, will ſet the beſt Fabricke<note n="c" place="margin">Dimittitur Concupiſcentia Carnis in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo, Non vt non ſit ſed vt non imputetur. Aug. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> ex Nuſtis</note> on fire. Therefore I haue deemed it not vnworthy the time and labour, to ſound the Syrces and ſhelfes which are to bee declined, of thoſe whoſe Soules would not be ſuncke in this deuouring<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor 7.9 2 Cor 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>Scylla.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which,</p>
            <p>The firſt is Idleneſſe and Sloath: For then and not till then ſins<note n="e" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>llo aeſtu Charibdis luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae ſalutem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, Ibiore Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineo ad pudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae perpetrands naufragia, Scyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſeu renidens libido blanditur: Hieron. ad Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> when hee ſent out <hi>Ioab</hi> to his wonted Warfare, and himſelfe walkes at eaſe in his Pallace; Which the Poet ſpyed by the eye of Nature.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quaeritur Aegiſthus quare ſit factus Adulter?</l>
               <l>In promptu cauſa eſt deſidioſus erat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Vnchaſt folly is for the moſt part begotte of an idle braine, and hatched in a lazy body, as our<note n="f" place="margin">D. Boyes ſuper Euang. d. <hi>15.</hi> p. Tr.</note> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Poſtiller obſerues (as hee doth all thinges verie ingenuouſly; Whereas,
<q>
                  <l>Otia ſi tollas periere Cupidinis arcus,</l>
                  <l>Contemptaequ, iacent, et ſine luce faces.<note n="e" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.1 to 6.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Cupid</hi> ſhoores in a ſlugge, and hits few but the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17950:24"/>ſloathfull: This therefore ſhould bee no ſmall care in all partes of the Kingdome, and in this renowned City, deſerues no ſmall commendations, That hee which <hi>will not worke, may not cate,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 3.10. But bee exterminated as a Citizen of <hi>Sodome, Who will hee ſloathfull in their Vocation,</hi> Ezechiel, 16.49. Or elſe bee committed to that Gymnoſophiſticall Diſcipline, Where hee ſhall render not an Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but a Diurnall Account of his Doinges: For as amongſt all the giftes of the Spirite, and all the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the Church, There are none for Idleneſſe, but all for Working <hi>and Edefying,</hi> Rom. 12.6. to 16. 1. Corinthians 12. Epheſians, 4.11.12. So amongeſt all the Eſtates, Degrees, and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Common-Weale, though there bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Ouerſeers, there muſt bee no Lookers on: for otherwiſe Idleneſſe will engender Adultery: So <hi>That when they are fedde to the full, by Troupes they will haunt Harlots Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Syrte to bee ſhunned, <hi>is filthie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, fooliſh talking, and ieſting, that is not conuenient,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fooliſh talking</note> Epheſ. 5.3, 4, <hi>For euill Wordes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners,</hi> 2. Cor. 15.33. <hi>Let therefore no corrupt Communication proceede out of your Mouth, but that which is good, to the vſe of Edifying, that it may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Grace to the Hearers,</hi> Epheſ. 4.29. A Leſſon needefull to bee learned in theſe our dayes, when not onely the elder ſorte amongſt the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 2.1.</note> raging multitude <hi>vſe their Tongues</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>as if there were no Lorde ouer them:</hi> or rather, as if<note n="c" place="margin">Tob, 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Aſmodeus,</hi> the Spirite of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17950:24"/>were Regent in them, but euen teach theyr Children ſo ſoone as they can Charter, lewde, laſciuious, and ribauld rimes: As if the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 8.2.</note> mouthes of Infants, Babes, and Sucklinges which were orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the prayſe of God, ſhould now onely ſerue for <hi>Cupids Cryers, Belzebubs Beadles,</hi> and <hi>Helles Herrolds;</hi> Whereupon it is no wonder, being ſo educated at the firſt, and<note n="b" place="margin">Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſeruabit odorem Teſtae diu. Horat. <hi>Wanton be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</hi>
               </note> ſeaſoned with ſinne, if when they are grown vp and ſedde to the full, they by <hi>Troupes haunt Harlots Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The thirde Rocke to bee retired from, If thou wilt not ſuffer Shippe-wracke by this ſinne, Is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Lookes, and light Behauiour: That the <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Syon may not walke with ſtretcht forth neckes and wanton Eyes, mincing as they goe, and making a tincke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with their feet,</hi> Iſai, 3.16. For if the Prince of the Apoſtles had beene made Iudge of ſuch, I doubte he would haue applyed this place vnto them,<note n="c" place="margin">Si vir, vel mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier ſe ornaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vt vultus hominum in ſe prouocaeuerit, et<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi nullum inde ſequatur dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num induium tamen patietur aternum, quia venenum attu lit, ſi fuiſſet qui biberet: Hieron: Auro &amp; Margaritis adornata, &amp; Monilibus ornamenta Mentis &amp; Corporis pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds lecunt: Cyprian: de Habit: Virg.</note> 
               <hi>They haue eyes ful of Adultery, and cannot ceaſe from ſinne,</hi> 2. Peter, 2.14. And vnleſſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> bee a Steward in ſuch a houſe; <hi>Putipher</hi> may well feare the looſing that one thing, which he hath onely reſerued; which if you will haue preſerued; thoſe prouocations, (that I may not ſay Proclamations) of Impurity, muſt be preuented.</p>
            <p>A fourth thing to be forborne, is the frequenting
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17950:25"/>lewde places,<note place="margin">Lewd Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</note> or aſſociating with laſciuious perſons: For<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 6.27.28.29.</note> 
               <hi>Can a man take fire in his boſome, and his cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes bee not burnt? Can one goe vpon hote Coales, and his feete not bee burnt? So hee that goeth into his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wife, Whoſoeuer toucheth her ſhall not bee Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 5.8.9</note> 
               <hi>Remooue thy way therefore farre from her, and come not nigh the doores of her houſe, leaſt thou giue thine honour vnto others, and thy ſtrength to the Cruell:</hi> For, <hi>Cum Peruerſo peruerteris,</hi> With the Peruerſe thou ſhalt be peruerted (as<note n="c" place="margin">Hieron.</note> the Father reades it) Pſalme, 18.26. And therefore if thou wilt eſcape the Hooke, then ſwallow not the bayte; for otherwiſe thou ſhalt not reſt, vntill thou haſt done euill, Prou. 4.16.</p>
            <p>The fift and laſt daungerous arriuing,<note place="margin">Drunkenneſſe</note> is at the Deepes of Drunkenneſſe, and vnſounded Shoare of Surfetting; Another of the ſupreame Implicit ſins, depending vpon Plentie; <hi>When hee fedde them to the full?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A vice ſo vile, ſo baſe, ſo beaſtlike, as that it<note n="d" place="margin">Fbrietas tudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium Rutonis obfuſeat, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones &amp; bella pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urat, robur &amp; Naturalem virtutem euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat, Infirmitatem generas, mortem naturalem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducit, Hugo, de Sancto Victor.</note> tranſſorms the ſoule, deformes the body, bereaues the Brayne; betrayes the ſtrengthe, deſiles the affection, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſeth the whole man, making the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ignorant, the ſtrong ſtaggering, the truſty troth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the vertuous vitious, and the preciſeft perſon, a Pander to the prophaneſt ſinne: Drunkennes as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerues) being the<note n="e" place="bottom">Flagitirrum omnium mater, Radix Criminum, Culparum materia, Origo vitiorum, Turbatio Capitis, ſubuerſio senſus, Tempeſtas Lingua, Procellae Corporis, Naufragium Caſtitams, &amp;c. Auguſtin. ad Sacr: Virg.</note> mother of miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17950:25"/>the matter that miniſters all miſchiefe, the roote of wretchedneſſe, the vent of vice, the Subuerter of the Senſes, the Confounder of the Capacity, rayſing aſtorme in the Tongue, Billowes in the Body, and Shippe-wracke in the ſoule, the loſſe of Time, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupter of Conuerſation, the diſcredite of Carriage, the Infamie of Honeſty, the Sincke that ſwallowes Chaſtitie, the Infirmity whoſe Phyſitian is Ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and the madneſſe whoſe Medicine is Miſery: Whereupon <hi>Salomon</hi> is ſo carefull to preuent the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger before it ſeaze, leaſt afterwardes it bee neyther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued with eaſe, nor abide alone with all mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry;<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 23.31.32.33.</note> 
               <hi>That hee will not haue a man looke vpon the Wine when it is Redde, when it giueth his colour in the Cuppe, or when it ſparkleth aright, leaſt at the laſt it bite him like a Serpent, and ſting hius like an Adder, cauſe his eyes to behold ſtrange Womeu, and his Hearte to vtter peruerſe thinges.</hi> When<note n="b" place="margin">Noe ad vnius borae ebrietatent nudauit ſemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia ſua, quae ad Sexcentos an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos contexerat. Hieron. Ep. <hi>1.</hi> ad Occan.</note> lay <hi>Noah</hi> vncoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but when hee was drunke, Gen. 9.21. When com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>Lot</hi> inceſt but in his Wine, Gen. 19.32. to 38. And when thought <hi>Dauids</hi> Arch-policy, the fitteſt time to vaile his Adultery, but at a deuice of drinking, 2, <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Sine Cerere et Libero friget Venus:</hi> For ſhe dwels onely at the Iuie-Buſh, But <hi>Ebrietas quid non defignat;</hi> It infecteth the Soule worſe then <hi>Sodome:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro. 23.29</hi> Aſſumit inter pocula anguſta certamina, &amp; malis exiſtenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cauſis aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n ram excitat rixam. Aug. vbi ſupr.</note> To omit the woes, ſorrowes, bablings, contentions, and woundes without cauſe which attend it, as alſo<note n="d" place="bottom">
                  <hi>1. Eſdr. 3 22.</hi> Refertur Alexandri Macedo tae exemplum qu Clituim chariſsimum ſibi as ſideliſsnnum inter epulas tranſfodit, &amp; intellecto facinore mori vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit. Sence. Ep. <hi>34.</hi> ad Lucil.</note> How men in their Cuppes forgette their loue to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17950:26"/>friendes, and raſhly draw their ſwordes: And howe,<note n="a" place="margin">Sam. 13.28</note> when mens harts are merry with wine, they are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſmitten to death: So that a<note n="b" place="margin">Iudith. 12.20 &amp; 13. to 9.</note> ſilly woman may ſlay the ſtrongeſt man of Armes, if <hi>Holifernes</hi> himſelfe bee made the Inſtance. To omitte, I ſay, theſe and a thouſand other Inconueniences, which are <hi>Appendix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> to this vice, And onely to inſiſt vpon the Affinity of it with that ſinne which in the preſent is propoſed for the effect of it.</p>
            <p>Is not Drunkenneſſe the mother Nurce and Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to Adulterie? Or at leaſt Laſciuiouſnes the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Luxurie? Is not<note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 20.1.</note> wine a mocker, and ſtrong drink raging? Let <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> who could forbear <hi>Vaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi> al the time of his feaſting, but muſt haue her brought foorth when his hart was merry with VVine, <hi>Eſther,</hi> 1.10, 11. And here theſe Iſraelites bee the Inſtance, who when they were fedde to the full, <hi>By troupes they haunt Harlots Houſes.</hi> And therefore as hee that will not be defiled, <hi>muſt not touch Puch,</hi> Eccleſ. 13.1. So hee that will not bee enflamed to vncleanneſſe muſt not onely take heed of being drunken with wine, wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, Epheſians 5.18. But euen auoyde keeping company with wine-bibbers, or riotous eaters of fleſh, <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 23.20.21. For as Pouerty is their <hi>Pediſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeque,</hi> ſo<note n="d" place="margin">Eſus carnium &amp; potus vini, ventriſque ſatu ritas Seminariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libulinis eſt, Ariſt. Ethie. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Chambering and wantonneſſe will be their aſſociate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13. Laſciuiouſneſſe. Luſts, riotings, and banquetings are ioyned by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Peter,</hi> 4.3. And will be ſeldome ſeuered by Apoſtataes; Doe wee not ſee by ordinary experience, the laſciuions ſteale to maintaine drunkenneſſe, when drunkenneſſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17950:26"/>was delighted in, only for the deſire of vncleannes? So<note n="a" place="margin">Luxuriae ad praeſins volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem deliniens, futuram non ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mt cogita epau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertatem Aug. doctr. Chriſt:</note> reiking in this riotouſnes, that they neuer wreake that woe which ſhall be vnto them which riſe vp earely to follow ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g drink, &amp; continue vntil they be enflamed, <hi>Iſal,</hi> 5.11. Whereby it comes to paſſe, that Hell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens her mouth wide, and they in multitudes deſcend into it, whileſt they ſo lie weltering in their wickednes, that they neuer conſider the curſe which ſhal fall vpon him, who giues his neighbour ſtrong drinke, and puts his bottle to him; and makes him drinke alſo, that he may looke on his nakedneſſe, <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.15.16. How hee ſhall be filled with ſhame in ſteade of glory, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe drinke alſo till his foreskinne be vncouered, how the cup of the Lordes right hand ſhall bee turned vnto him, and ſhamefull ſhewing ſhall bee his honour. But<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 50.22</note> oh would they would conſider this, that thus forget God, leaſt hee take them away in a Time, when there is none to deliuer them. Would I ſay, they would conſider with Saint <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> that <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ad bibendum pronus fuerit, velin Conuiuio ſuo alios ſuos adiurauit, pro ſe &amp; pro ipſis in Die Iudicij reus erit.</hi> Whoſoeuer is proue himſelfe, or prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth others to drinking, ſhal anſwere both for his own, and their offence, at the day of iudgement, which might teach them to take heed vnto themſelues, that their harts may not at any time bee ouercharged with ſurfetting &amp; drunkennes, &amp; ſo <hi>that fearefull day of the Lord</hi> (or their death, <hi>come vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnawares,</hi> Lu. 21.34.35. for as a ſnare ſhal it com vpon all ſuch inhabiters of the earth; yea with all the ſnares &amp; puniſhments which are due vnto Adultery, that iſſues from this ſinne of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17950:27"/>drunkenneſſe, Which is the next obiect of our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</p>
            <p>What puniſhments are due to offenders in it?<note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> Wherein to omitte the particular perſonall paines of the Body, which God inflicteth according to his own pleaſure, anſwerable oftentimes to the quality of the Conſtitution, or<note n="a" place="margin">Wiſd. 11.15.16.</note> correſpondent to the forme of the offence, when <hi>Occultam culpam ſequitur aperta per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſsio,</hi> becauſe theſe are not alwayes apparently inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all Offenders. And thoſe of which Antiquitie durſt aueare that.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quatuor his poenis punietur quiſquis Adulter,</l>
               <l>Aut erit hic pauper, aut hic ſubita morietur,</l>
               <l>Aut aliquod ſubito franget de corpore membrum,</l>
               <l>Aut cadet in famam qua debet carcere trudi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That euery Adulterer ſhall bee ouertaken with one of theſe foure extremities, 1. Eyther he ſhall be poore and begge his bread, yea and ſeeke it out of deſolate places; 2. Or elſe hee ſhall die ſuddenly, and bee vnexpectedly cut off in the day that he thinkes not of it: 3. Or elſe hee ſhall haue his bones ſhatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and broken a ſunder in his ſecurity, euen as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breakes and heweth wood vpon the earth: ſo that he ſhall liue ſo miſerably, as hee ſhall ſeeke death, and not finde it; That body being the greateſt griefe and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnto him, which before hee pampered to followe the delightes and luſtes of the fleſh, 4. Or elſe hee ſhall fall into ſuch reproach and infamy, that hee
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17950:27"/>ſhall bee deſeruedly caſt into priſon for his Impiety To omit (I ſay) theſe, Wee will inferre as ineuitable, That as the Lepreians carried thoſe which were de prehended for the Fact, three dayes bound through-the City, and afterwardes deſpiſed them during their life time: So the Apoſtle appointed amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that if there were any fornicator amongſt them hee ſhould bee bound with the chaines of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and publiſhed through the Synagogues, That they ſhould haue no commerce nor company with him, 1. Cor. 5, 11. And as in the old Worlde,<note n="a" place="margin">Non haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes cum eis ſocietatem vel communione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Aq: in Ep.</note> they which defiled themſelues with ſtrange fleſh, were reſerued vnto the vengeance of eternall fire, <hi>Iude,</hi> 7. So in this latter age, all Adulterers and vncleane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are lyable to the Lake that burnes with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8. Where, <hi>Pro breui voluptate perpetua poena;</hi> For a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pleaſure they ſhall ſuffer many millions of paine, (as Saint <hi>Bede</hi> ſayth) yea, and that which is, if any thing can bee, yet more fearefull; not onely them ſelues, but euen their poſterity, which are the iſſue of ſuch vnlawfull ſeede, yea, and the goods which are gotten by ſuch vnlawfull meanes ſhall all bee conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and vtterly rooted out, one moneth ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them, their ſtrange Children, and all their por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Hoſea,</hi> 5.7. For the multiplying broode of the vngodly ſhall not thrine, nor take deepe rooting from Baſtard ſhppes, nor lay any faſt foundation; for though they flouriſh in branches for a time, yet ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not faſt, they ſhall bee ſhaken with the VVinde, and through the force of the wind they ſhal be rooted
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17950:28"/>out: The vnperfect branches ſhall bee broken off, their fruit vnprofitable, not ripe to eate, yea meet for nothing: For children begotten of vnlawfull beds are witneſſes of wickedneſſe againſt their Parents in theyr Tryall, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 4.3.4.5.6. For howſoeuer to ſome this ſeeme ſo ſweete a ſinne, as that they will not leaue it till they dye, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 23.17. yet as you may reade (and it is well worth the reading to this purpoſe) in the ſame Chapter to the 27. verſe. <hi>The Whoremonger ſhall bee taken in a time when hee ſuſpecteth not, and puniſhed in the ſtreetes, And the wife that leaues her husband, and bringeth in hyre by another, ſhall bee brought out into the Congregation, that Inquiſition may bee made of her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who ſhall take no roote, And ſhee ſhall leaue her memory to bee curſed, and her reproach ſhall not be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who would not therefore feare this fatall fault, and affrighted, take vp Saint <hi>Hieromes</hi> exclamation againſt this ſinne, <hi>O lgnis infernalis, Luxuria, Cuius materia Gula, Cuius flamma ſuperbia, Cuius Scintillae praua colloquia, cuius fumus infamia, cuius cinis immun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditia, cuius finis Gehenna:</hi> O thou infernall fire of Luſt, whoſe fuell is full feeding, whoſe flame is proud flouriſhing, whoſe ſparckles are ribald ſpeaking, whoſe fume is Infamie, whoſe aſhes vncleanneſſe, Whoſe Vrne is hell, and whoſe extinguiſhing eternall bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, whoſe kindling occaſionates ſuch a Counter-Plea to mans Pardon, that the Almighty thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerates his offences: <hi>How ſhall I pardon thee for this? Thy children haue forſaken mee, and ſworne by thoſe that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17950:28"/>are no Gods, and when I fedde them to the full, by troupes they haunt Harlots Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I deſcend to the firſt aggrauation, which is Their Impudency; <hi>By troupes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impudency.</note> Cuſtome hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed them ſo ſhameleſſe in ſinning, as that they not onely proclaime theyr impiety in the eares of theyr Abettors; and<note n="a" place="margin">They were as fed horſes, &amp;c. ver. 8.</note> beaſtlike communicate their conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination with their Aſſociates, but euen publiſh their impuritie to the eyes of the offended obſeruers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring their ſinnes as <hi>Sodeme,</hi> and hide it not, <hi>Iſay,</hi> 3.9. But like <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosby</hi> in the very doore of theyr Tents, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> wept before the <hi>Taberuacle,</hi> Numb: 25.6. Or like <hi>Abſolon,</hi> that pitcht his tents vpon the very roofe of the Pallace, to demonſtrate in the eyes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> his corrupting of his Fathers Fathers Concubines, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.22. So they not onely in the Euening, or at Twilight, or in the blacke and darke of the night, when they may flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felues that none doe ſee them: Like <hi>Solomons Foole with his Female, Prou.</hi> 7.9. to 1. But euen then (that I may not ſay now) when the Congregations are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to ſorrow for this ſinne, doe not onely<note n="b" place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> 
               <hi>ſtand ſingle by the Walles of the ſtreetes, and in the doores of theyr Houſes,</hi> but <hi>euen by troupes haunt Harlots Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Adeo, qui cum periit ſemel redire neſcit, periit pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor:</hi> So farre hath ſhame (which being loſt can ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome be regayned) forſaken them, &amp; ſo faſt flock they by troupes vnto thoſe Houſes, Where ſhameleſſe is the Sewer. Whoſe vnparralelde Impudency not once
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17950:29"/>to be vnapparelled for the vgly apparitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſt it ſhould enforce me to breake the bounds of modeſty, in rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vp thoſe deunes of darkeneſſe, I will onely Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematically deſcribe vnto you a threefold ſituation, of ſuch ſinckes of ſinne, that ſo you may the ſpeedili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er addreſſe an Inquiſition for the ſuppreſſing of them, (if any there be) as many there were in <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt, <hi>Ioſh,</hi> 2.1.15. <hi>Vpon the towne wall, where they had their ſecret paſſage through Windowes.</hi> 2. The ſecond, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.4. <hi>In a Valley by a Brooke ſide, where they might haue entercourſe without obſeruing.</hi> 3. The third, 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3.16, <hi>A couple of Victua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in the City, where vnder pretente of Repaſt, they might repoſe more freely, And ſo by troupes aſſemble them ſelues in Harlots Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſembled Here,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pertinacity.</note> Is the laſt circumſtance which aggrauates this ſin, which is Pertinacity: For as woe ſhall be vnto thoſe which haue loſt<note n="a" place="margin">Greg. Mag: mort in Iob. lib. <hi>1</hi> ſuper his verbis: Sic faciebat Iob aſsi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue.</note> 
               <hi>Perſeueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian;</hi> Theyr Perſeuerance is good, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.14. So no leſſe wee ſhall bee vnto thoſe, who will not leaue <hi>Pertinaciam,</hi> their Pertinacity in euill. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Looke how without Perſeuerance, no Vertue is auayleable vpon reuolting: So without Pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, no ſinne is vnpardonable, vpon Repenting: And therefore if any haue fallen<note n="b" place="margin">The Kinges Bible reades, ouertaken in a fault, &amp;c.</note> vpon occaſion (as the Apoſtle calles, it) <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. That is to ſay, Through<note n="c" place="margin">Heming in loc. Luther in Gal</note> Infirmity into any of theſe ſinnes: Let him take heede how hee haunt them, that is to ſay,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17950:29"/>continue obſtinately.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 9.21.</note> 
               <hi>Noah,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen 19.33. to 36.</note> 
               <hi>Loth,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 38.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>Iudath,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2. Sam. 11.4 15, &amp; 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Math. 26.70. to 75.</note> 
               <hi>Peter;</hi> They all fell; but they haunted them not, And peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as <hi>Iſidore</hi> affirmes; <hi>Vtile ſit arrogantibus deſeri à Deo, quatenus ſuae infirmitatis, conſcii ad humilitatem redeant, vt humiles poſt lapſum exiſtant,</hi> God may ſee it ſometimes profitable for the proud to bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of him for a ſeaſon, to the end that experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally vnderſtanding theyr owne inability, they may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theyr fall humble themſelues with the greater fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie. But let them take heede, <hi>That they draw not iniquity with coardes of vanity, and ſinne as it were with Cartroapes.</hi> Iſai. 5.18. That they haunt not that by which they haue harmde: For then Woe ſhall bee vnto them. Whereas otherwiſe if they forſake their ſinne, conuert and cry for merey<note n="f" place="margin">Let no No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatian or Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane ſay, as it was obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> That wee giue a gappe to ſinne, when wee offer a hauen of ſafety to euery repentant ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for to thoſe that deny it, we reply with <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtus. Erege tibi ſcalum Aceſt, &amp; adcoelum ſolus afcende:</hi> Erect a Stayre <hi>Ateſius,</hi> for thy ſelfe, and climbe to Heauen alone without a ſlippe, So <hi>Meridith Hanmir</hi> tranſlates <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 42. <hi>vide Epiphan. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Hareſ.</hi> 59. <hi>Socrat lib.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 7. 2. <hi>Aug. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m:</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia nunquam claudet gremium redeunti: And Chriſt came not to call the Righteous but ſinners to Repentance,</hi> Math, 9.13. Yea; he will admit Repenting Publicanes and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots into the kingdom of heauen before ſelf-Iuſtifying Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Math.</hi> 21.31. Where elſe had <hi>Tamar</hi> ſtoode in the<note n="g" place="bottom">Math. 1.3.</note> Line of Chriſt for all her<note n="h" place="bottom">Gen. 38.25.</note> Tokens: What<note n="i" place="bottom">Ioſh. 2.18.21.</note> redde liſt could haue reſcued <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi>
               <note n="k" place="bottom">Ioſh. 6.17.20.</note> when the Walles of <hi>Ierico</hi> fell downe flat, to giue the enemies entrance? What<note n="l" place="bottom">Luc. 7.38.</note> Riuers of teares might haue waſted <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> from<note n="m" place="bottom">Ioh. 8 4. to 12.</note> the cape
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17950:30"/>of condemation, ſo neare vnto the hauen of Heauen, As be to the firſt that beheld<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 20, 15.16</note> our <hi>SAVIOVRS</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: Yea what<note n="b" place="margin">1. Reg. 5.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Abanah, Pharphar</hi> or <hi>Iordan</hi> could haue purified all the Fornicators, Idolaters, Adulterers, effeminate Perſons, Abuſers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with mankind, Theeues, Couetous Perſons, Drunkards, Raylors and Extortioners, which without Repentance were not capable of the Kingdome of Heauen; yea, (and to bee bolde in the Apoſtles wordes to conuerted Chriſtians) Euen ſome of you, which ſomtime were ſuch, but that after Repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>you are now waſhed, and ſanctified, and iuſtified, in the Name of the LORD IESVS CHRIST, and by the Spirit of our GOD,</hi> 1. Cor. 6.9.10.11. Oh therfore whoſoeuer you be that haue<note n="c" place="margin">Wiſd 5.7.</note> wearied your ſelues in the way of theſe wickedneſſes and deſtruction, and haue not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto knowne the way of the Lord: Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſions whereby yee haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and make you a new heart, and a new ſpirite, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or why will yee dye O houſe of Iſrael, ſith I haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the death of him that dyeth,</hi> (ſayeth the Lord, <hi>Wherefore turne your ſelues and liue yee,</hi> Ezech. 18.31 <hi>Returne, Returne,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rites quippe captiuae interpretatue, &amp;c. Que infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis iugo a Daemembus, captiuatur, &amp;c. Greg. Mag. in Cant:</note> 
               <hi>O Shunamite, Returne, returne, that he may looke vpon thee,</hi> Cant. 6.13. <hi>Euen with that eye of Compaſſion, by which, when none other pitties thee, yet hee may ſay vnto thee, Liue,</hi> Ezech. 16.5.6. And whileſt thou leaueſt thy old haunts,<note n="e" place="margin">Leuit. 19.30</note> &amp; frequenteſt his houſe, forſakeſt thy ſwearing, and<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 42.4.</note> reuorenceſt his Sanctuary, turneſt thy Troupes that haunted Harlots Houſes<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal: <hi>42.</hi> vbi ſu</note> into multitudes that keepe his Holy day; thy ſloath
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17950:30"/>into his ſeruice, thy wantonneſſe to warmneſſe, thy diſobedience to dutifulneſſe, thy<note n="a" place="margin">Ioel. 27.19.</note> Idolatry to deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thy prophane ſpeeches to prayſes, thy Periury to Prayers, thy<note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 21 34. Mark. 13.33</note> drunkenneſſe to watch for the day of Doome: and thy<note n="c" place="margin">Greg Mag. homan Aug.</note> ſinnes to ſacrifices, He will finde a meanes, <hi>How to pardon thee for this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which God graunt of his mercies for his Sonnes Merites, through the powerfull Operation of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; which only prepares man to Repentance: To which Trinity in Vnity, and Vnity in Trinity, be aſcribed<note n="d" place="margin">Apoc. 4.11. &amp; 5.12.13</note> al glory, power, prayſe, might, and Maieſtie by the conuerts in this Church vpon Earth, as there is<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 15.10.</note> Reioiſing at their Conuerſion, by the Angels in that Church in Heauen, from this time forth for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
